<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The clear sun-shine of the gospel breaking forth upon the Indians in Nevv-England. Or, An historicall narration of Gods wonderfull workings upon sundry of the Indians, both chief governors and common-people, in bringing them to a willing and desired submission to the ordinances of the gospel; and framing their hearts to an earnest inquirie after the knowledge of God the Father, and of Jesus Christ the Saviour of the world. / By Mr. Thomas Shepard minister of the gospel of Jesus Christ at Cambridge in New-England.</title>
            <author>Shepard, Thomas, 1605-1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93076</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3109</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E431_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206115</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865295</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865295</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117534</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93076)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117534)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 68:E431[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The clear sun-shine of the gospel breaking forth upon the Indians in Nevv-England. Or, An historicall narration of Gods wonderfull workings upon sundry of the Indians, both chief governors and common-people, in bringing them to a willing and desired submission to the ordinances of the gospel; and framing their hearts to an earnest inquirie after the knowledge of God the Father, and of Jesus Christ the Saviour of the world. / By Mr. Thomas Shepard minister of the gospel of Jesus Christ at Cambridge in New-England.</title>
                  <author>Shepard, Thomas, 1605-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Cotes for John Bellamy at the three golden Lions in Cornhill near the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March 8th 1647"; the 8 in imprint date is crossed out and replaced with a 7.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Indians of North America --  Massachusetts --  Missions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian converts --  New England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117534:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117534:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Clear Sun-ſhine of the Goſpel BREAKING FORTH UPON THE INDIANS IN NEW-ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>OR, An Hiſtoricall Narration of Gods Wonderfull Workings upon ſundry of the INDIANS, both chief Governors and Common-people, in bringing them to a willing and deſired ſubmiſſion to the Ordinances of the Goſpel; and framing their hearts to an earneſt inquirie after the knowledge of God the Father, and of Jeſus Chriſt the Saviour of the World.</p>
            <p>By Mr. THOMAS SHEPARD Miniſter of the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt at <hi>Cambridge</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iſaiah 2 2, 3.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>And it ſhall come to paſſe in the laſt dayes, that the mountain of the Lords houſe ſhall bee eſtabliſhed in the top of the mountains, and ſhall bee exalted above the bills; and all Nations ſhall flow unto it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And many people ſhal go and ſay, Come ye and let us go up to the mountain of the Lord, to the houſe of the God of Jacob, and he will teach us of his wayes, and we will walk in his paths: for out of Zion ſhall go forth the Law, and the word of the Lord from Jeruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Cotes</hi> for <hi>John Bellamy</hi> at the three golden Lions in <hi>Cornhill</hi> near the Royall Exchange, 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:117534:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117534:2"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RABLE</hi> THE LORDS &amp; COMMONS <hi>Aſſembled</hi> In High Court of Parliament.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe <hi>few</hi> ſheets <hi>preſent</hi> unto your view a ſhort but welcome <hi>diſcourſe</hi> of the viſitations of the <hi>moſt High</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſaddeſt ſpectacles of <hi>degeneracy</hi> upon earth, The <hi>poore Indian People:</hi> the <hi>diſtance</hi> of place, (if our <hi>ſpirits</hi> be right) will be no <hi>leſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> of the mercy, nor of our <hi>thankefulneſse,</hi> That <hi>Chriſt</hi> is glorified, that the <hi>Goſpel</hi> doth any where find <hi>footing;</hi> and ſucceſſe is a <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> as well worthy the <hi>praiſe</hi> of the <hi>Saints</hi> on Earth, as the <hi>joy</hi> of the <hi>Angels</hi> in heaven. The <hi>report</hi> of this mercy is <hi>firſt</hi> made to you, who are the <hi>Repreſentative</hi> of this Nation, That in you <hi>England</hi> might bee ſtirred up, to be
<pb facs="tcp:117534:3"/> Rejoycers in, and Advancers of theſe promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing beginnings. And becauſe to You an <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count</hi> is <hi>first</hi> due of the <hi>ſucceſſe</hi> of the Goſpel in thoſe <hi>darke</hi> corners of the World, which have been ſo much <hi>inlightned</hi> by Your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, <hi>enlivened</hi> by Your reſolutions, <hi>encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged</hi> by Your fore paſt indeavours for God, &amp; hope ſtil being parts of Your ſelves, to be <hi>further</hi> ſtrengthned by Your benigne aſpects and bountifull influences on them.</p>
            <p>The preſent <hi>troubles</hi> have not ſo far <hi>obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated</hi> and worn out the ſad <hi>miſpreſſions</hi> which <hi>former</hi> times have made upon our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, but we can <hi>ſadly</hi> remember thoſe <hi>deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive</hi> deſignes which were on foot, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed on for the <hi>Introduction</hi> of ſo great <hi>evils</hi> both into <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State;</hi> In order to which it was the <hi>endeavour</hi> of the <hi>Contrivers</hi> and <hi>Promoters</hi> of thoſe deſignes, <hi>to waſt</hi> the number of the godly, as thoſe who would never be brought to <hi>comply</hi> in ſuch deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive enterpriſes; which was attempted by <hi>baniſhing</hi> and <hi>forcing</hi> ſome abroad, by <hi>bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening</hi> and <hi>afflicting</hi> all at home. Among thoſe who <hi>taſted</hi> of the <hi>firſt,</hi> I ſay not the <hi>worſt</hi> ſort of their cruelty, were theſe our
<pb facs="tcp:117534:3"/> 
               <hi>Brethren,</hi> who to enjoy the <hi>liberties</hi> of the Goſpel, were <hi>content</hi> to ſit downe, and pitch their <hi>tents</hi> in the <hi>utmoſt</hi> parts of the Earth, hoping that there they might be out of the <hi>reach</hi> of their malice, as they were aſſured they were beyond the <hi>bounds</hi> of their love. God who doth often make mans <hi>evill</hi> of ſin, ſerviceable to the <hi>advancement</hi> of the <hi>riches</hi> of his owne Grace; The moſt <hi>horrid</hi> act that ever was done by the <hi>ſonnes</hi> of men, the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rther</hi> of Chriſt, God made <hi>ſerviceable</hi> to the higheſt <hi>purpoſes</hi> of Grace and mercy that ever <hi>came</hi> upon his breaſt; That God doth ſhew that hee had <hi>mercifull</hi> ends, in this their <hi>malicious</hi> purpoſe: as hee ſuffer'd <hi>Paul</hi> to be caſt into priſon, to <hi>convert</hi> the <note place="margin">Act 16. 30, 33, 34. Acts. 8. 1. 11</note> Jaylor, to be ſhip wrackt at <hi>Melita,</hi> to <hi>preach</hi> to the <hi>barbarous,</hi> ſo he <hi>ſuffer'd</hi> their way to be <hi>stopped</hi> up here, and their perſons to be <hi>baniſhed</hi> hence, that hee might <hi>open</hi> a paſſage for them in the Wilderneſſe, and make them <hi>inſtruments</hi> to draw ſoules to him, who had been ſo long <hi>eſtranged</hi> from him.</p>
            <p>It was the end of the <hi>adverſary</hi> to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, but Gods to <hi>propagate</hi> the Goſpel; theirs to <hi>ſmother</hi> and put out the light, Gods to <hi>communicate</hi> and diſperſe it to the
<pb facs="tcp:117534:4"/> 
               <hi>utmoſt</hi> corners of the Earth; that as one ſaith of <hi>Paul, his blindneſſe gave light to the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>whole World,</hi> ſo we hope God will make their diſtance and <hi>estrangedneſſe</hi> from us, a meanes of <hi>bringing</hi> many near and in to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with him.</p>
            <p>Indeed <hi>along time</hi> it was before God let them ſee any <hi>farther</hi> end of their comming o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, then to <hi>preſerve</hi> their conſciences, <hi>cheriſh</hi> their Graces, <hi>provide</hi> for their ſuſtenance: But when <hi>Providences</hi> invited their return, he let them <hi>know</hi> it was for ſome farther Arrand that hee <hi>brought</hi> them thither, giving them ſome <hi>Bunches</hi> of Grapes, ſome <hi>Cluſters</hi> of Figs in <hi>earneſt</hi> of the proſperous <hi>ſucceſſe</hi> of their endeavours upon thoſe <hi>poor outcaſts:</hi> The <hi>ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ends of the earth are <hi>deſigned</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to be <hi>in time</hi> the poſſeſſions of Chriſt; And <hi>hee ſends his Miniſters into every place where he himſelf intends to come,</hi> and take poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion. Where the <hi>Ministery</hi> is the <hi>Harbinger</hi> and goes before, Chriſt and <hi>Grace</hi> will <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly</hi> follow after.</p>
            <p>This little we ſee is <hi>ſomething</hi> in hand, to <hi>earneſt</hi> to us thoſe things which are in hope; ſomething in <hi>poſſeſſion,</hi> to aſſure us of the <hi>reſt</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:117534:4"/> in Promiſe, when the <hi>ends</hi> of the earth ſhall ſee his <note place="margin">Pſal. 22. 27. Rev. 11. 15. Pſal. 72. 8, 9, 10, 11.</note> glory, and <hi>the Kingdomes of the world ſhall become the Kingdomes of the Lord and his Chriſt, when hee ſhall have Dominion from Sea to Sea, and they that dwell in the wilderneſſe ſhall bow before him.</hi> And if the <hi>dawn</hi> of the <hi>morning</hi> be ſo delightfull, what will the <hi>clear</hi> day be? If the <hi>firſt fruits</hi> be ſo precious, what wil the <hi>whole harveſt</hi> be? if ſome <hi>beginnings</hi> be ſo ful of joy, what will it be when God ſhall <hi>perform</hi> his <hi>whole</hi> work, when <hi>the whole earth ſhall be full of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <note place="margin">Iſa. 11. 9. 10.</note> of the Lord, as the waters cover the Sea,</hi> and Eaſt and Weſt ſhal ſing together the ſong of the Lamb?</p>
            <p>In <hi>order</hi> to this what doth God <hi>require</hi> of us, but that we ſhould <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> the hands, <hi>incourage</hi> the hearts of thoſe who are at <hi>work</hi> for him, <hi>conflicting</hi> with difficulties, <hi>wreſtling</hi> with diſcouragements, to <hi>ſpread</hi> the Goſpel, &amp; in that, the <hi>ſame</hi> and honor of this Nation, to the <hi>utmoſt</hi> ends of the earth? It was the <hi>deſign</hi> of your <hi>enemies</hi> to make them <hi>little,</hi> let it be your <hi>endevor</hi> to <hi>make</hi> them <hi>great,</hi> their <hi>greatneſſe</hi> is your ſtrength. Their enemies threatned <hi>their</hi> hands ſhould <hi>reach</hi> them for evil, God <hi>diſappointed</hi> them; And let your <hi>hands</hi> reach them now for good; there is enough in them to ſpeak then fit <hi>objects</hi> of your incouragement, they are men of <hi>choice</hi> ſpirits, not <hi>frighted</hi> with dangers, <hi>ſoftned</hi> with allurements, nor
<pb facs="tcp:117534:5"/> 
               <hi>diſcouraged</hi> with difficulties, <hi>preparing</hi> the way of the Lord in thoſe <hi>unpaſſable</hi> places of the earth, dealing with ſuch <hi>whom</hi> they are to <hi>make</hi> men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can <hi>make</hi> them Chriſtians. They are ſuch who are <hi>impreſsed</hi> for your ſervice in the <hi>ſervice</hi> of Chriſt, can <hi>ſtand</hi> alone, but deſire to have <hi>depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> on you, they feare not the <hi>malice</hi> of their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emies, but <hi>deſire</hi> the countenance and incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their friends; And ſhal your <hi>Honors</hi> in <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration</hi> of their <hi>former</hi> ſufferings, their <hi>preſent</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and <hi>reall</hi> deſervings, <hi>help the day of ſmall things among them;</hi> ſhal you intereſt them in your aſſiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as you are intereſted in their affections, you wil thereby not only <hi>further</hi> theſe <hi>beginnings</hi> of God by <hi>incouraging</hi> their hearts, and <hi>ſtrengthning</hi> their hands to <hi>work</hi> for him, but alſo (as we humbly conceive) much add to the <hi>comfort</hi> of your owne <hi>accounts</hi> in the day of the Lord, and lay greater obligations on them <hi>yet more</hi> to <hi>pray</hi> for you, to <hi>promote</hi> your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and together with us your <hi>unworthy ſervants</hi> to <hi>write down</hi> themſelves,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours humbly devotedin the ſervice of the Goſpel.
<list>
                     <item>Stephen Marſhall</item>
                     <item>Jeremy Whitaker</item>
                     <item>Edm. calamy</item>
                     <item>William Greenbill</item>
                     <item>John Downam</item>
                     <item>Philip Nye</item>
                     <item>Syd. Symptſon</item>
                     <item>William Carler</item>
                     <item>The. Goodwin</item>
                     <item>The. Caſe</item>
                     <item>Simeon Aſbe</item>
                     <item>Samuel Bolton.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:117534:5"/>
            <head>TO THE Godly and Well affected of this Kingdome of <hi>England;</hi> who pray for, and rejoyce in, the thrivings of the Goſpel of our <hi>LORD JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F ever thou hadſt experience of this day of power, theſe viſitations of Chriſt upon thine own ſpirit; I ſuppoſe thee to be one who haſt <hi>embarqu'd</hi> many prayers for the <hi>ſucceſſe</hi> of the Goſpel in theſe <hi>darke corners</hi> of the earth to <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> thy faith, <hi>inlarge</hi> thy heart, and aſſure thy ſoul that God is <hi>a God hearing prayers:</hi> An <hi>account</hi> is here given to thee of the <hi>conqueſts</hi> of the Lord Ieſus upon theſe poor out-caſts, who have thus long been eſtranged from him, ſpilt like <hi>water</hi> upon the ground and none to gather them. Formerly thou had, <hi>The Day-break,</hi> ſome <hi>dawnings</hi> of light, after along and black night of darkenes, here thou ſeeſt <hi>the ſun is up,</hi> which wee hope <hi>will rejoice like the ſtrong man to run its race,</hi> ſcattering thoſe thick clouds of darkneſſe, and <hi>ſhining</hi> brighter and brighter <hi>till it come to a perfect day.</hi> Theſe few ſheerts give thee ſome <hi>foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> for ſuch thoughts, and ſome further <hi>incouragements</hi> to wait &amp; pray for the <hi>accompliſhment</hi> of ſuch things. Here thou mayſt ſee, the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> is precious, <hi>the feet of them who bring glad ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings beautifull, Ordinances</hi> deſired, the <hi>Word</hi> frequented andattended, the <hi>Spirit</hi> alſo going forth in <hi>power</hi> and efficacy with it, in <hi>awakening</hi> and <hi>humbling</hi> of them, drawing forth thoſe <hi>affections</hi> of ſorrow, and expreſſions of <hi>tears</hi> in abundance, which no tortures or <hi>extremities</hi> were ever obſerved to <hi>force</hi> from them, with <hi>lamenting:</hi> we read here, their leaving of ſinne, they <hi>forſake</hi> their <hi>former</hi> evill wayes, and ſet up <hi>fences</hi> never to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne,
<pb facs="tcp:117534:6"/> by making <hi>laws</hi> for the <hi>puniſhment</hi> of thoſe ſins wherein they have lived, and to which they have been ſo much addicted. They ſet up <hi>prayers</hi> in their families <hi>morning</hi> and <hi>evening,</hi> and are in <hi>earneſt</hi> in them; And with more <hi>affection</hi> they <hi>crave</hi> Gods bleſsing upon a little p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rched corn, <hi>&amp; Indian</hi> ſtalks, then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of us do upon our greateſt plenty and abundance. They reſt on the Lords day, and make laws for the <hi>obſervation</hi> of it, whereinthey <hi>meet</hi> together to pray &amp; inſtruct one another in the things of God, which have been <hi>communicated</hi> to them. They renounce their <hi>diabolicall</hi> Charmes and Charmers, and many of thoſe who were <hi>practitioners</hi> in theſe ſinfull and ſoul-undoing Arts, being made naked, <hi>convinced</hi> and aſhamed of their evill, <hi>forſake</hi> their may, and betake themſelves to prayer, preferring the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ma. 26. 16. Incantario, muſhtatio. ler. 8. 17. Ecclef. 10. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Charm,</hi> before their <hi>diabolical Spells:</hi> herein God making good that promiſe Zeph. <hi>2. 11. I will famiſh al the Gods of the earth,</hi> (which he doth by withdrawing the worſhippers, and throwing contempt upon the worſhip) <hi>And men ſhal worſhip me alone e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one from his place, even all the Iſles of the Heathens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe are <hi>hopefull preſages</hi> that God is <hi>going</hi> out in his <hi>power</hi> and grace to <hi>conquer</hi> a people to himſelf; That he begins to caſt an <hi>owning</hi> look on them, whom he hath ſo long <hi>neglected</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 14. 16. Acts 17. 30. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> &amp; <hi>deſpiſed.</hi> And indeed God may wel <hi>ſeek</hi> out for other <hi>ground</hi> to ſow the ſeed of his <hi>Ordinances</hi> upon, ſeeing the <hi>ground</hi> where it hath been <hi>ſown</hi> hath brought forth no <hi>better</hi> fruit to him, he may well <hi>be peak</hi> another people to himſelf, ſeeing he <hi>finds</hi> no better <hi>entertainment</hi> among the people he hath <hi>eſpouſed</hi> to him, and that by ſo many <hi>mercies, priviledges, indeerments, ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> We have as many <hi>ſad ſymptomes</hi> of <hi>a declining,</hi> as theſe poor outcaſts have <hi>glad preſages</hi> of a <hi>Riſing</hi> Sun among them. The <hi>Ordinances</hi> are as much <hi>contemned</hi> here, as <hi>frequente</hi> there, the <hi>Miniſtery</hi> as much <hi>diſcouraged</hi> here, as <hi>embraced</hi> thre; <hi>Religion</hi> as much derided, the <hi>ways</hi> of godlineſs as much <hi>ſcorned</hi> here, as they can be <hi>wiſhed</hi> and deſired there; generally wee are <hi>ſick</hi> of plenty, wee ſurfet of our abundance, the worſt ofSurfets, and with our <hi>loathed Manna</hi> and <hi>diſdained</hi> food, God
<pb facs="tcp:117534:6"/> 
               <hi>preparing</hi> them a <hi>Table</hi> in the wildernes; where our <hi>ſatieties,</hi> wil be their <hi>ſufficiencies;</hi> our <hi>complaints,</hi> their <hi>contents;</hi> our <hi>bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> their <hi>comforts;</hi> if he cannot have an <hi>England</hi> here, he can have an <hi>England</hi> there: &amp; <hi>baptize</hi> &amp; adopt them into thoſe <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges,</hi> which wee have <hi>looked</hi> upon as our burthens. We have <hi>ſad decayes</hi> upon us, we are a <hi>revolting</hi> Nation, a people <hi>guilty</hi> of great <hi>defection</hi> from God. Some fall from the <hi>worſhip</hi> of God to their old <hi>ſuperſtitions,</hi> and corrupt worſhip, ſaying with thoſe in Ieremy, <hi>It was better with us then now.</hi> Some fall from the <hi>doctrin</hi> of grace to errors, ſome to <hi>damnable,</hi> others to <hi>defiling</hi> ſome to <hi>deſtructive,</hi> others to <hi>corruptive</hi> opinions. Some fal from <hi>profeſſed</hi> ſeeming holynes, to fin &amp; profanenes: who like <hi>blazing</hi> comets did ſhine <hi>bright</hi> for a time, but after have <hi>ſet</hi> in a <hi>night</hi> of darknes. We have many <hi>ſad ſymptomes</hi> on us, we <hi>decay</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all the <hi>means</hi> of nouriſhment, are <hi>barren</hi> under all Gods <hi>s;owings, dry</hi> under al the <hi>dews,</hi> droppings ſhowres of heaven, like that Country whereof <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> ſpeak, <hi>where drought cauſeth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, imbres pulverem.</note> 
               <hi>dirt, and ſhowres cauſeth duſt.</hi> And what doth God <hi>threaten</hi> herein, but to <hi>remove</hi> the <hi>Candleſticks,</hi> to take away the goſpel, that <hi>pretious</hi> Goſpel, the <hi>ſtreams</hi> whereof have brought ſo many <hi>ſhips</hi> laden with bleſsings to our ſhoar, that Goſpel under the <hi>ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow</hi> whereof we have <hi>ſate</hi> down and been <hi>refreſhed</hi> theſe many years? where the <hi>power</hi> is loſt, God will not <hi>long</hi> continue the <hi>form,</hi> where the <hi>heat</hi> is gone, he wil not <hi>long</hi> continue the light. The <hi>temple</hi> did not <hi>preſerve</hi> the laws when their <hi>hearts</hi> were the <hi>Synagogues</hi> of Satan, nor ſhall any <hi>outward priviledge</hi> hold us up, when the <hi>inward power</hi> is down in our ſpirits. God hath <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken</hi> other <hi>Churches</hi> as eminent as ever <hi>England</hi> was: where are the <hi>churches</hi> of <hi>Aſia,</hi> once <hi>famous</hi> for the goſpel, for general <hi>Councels,</hi> now places for <hi>Zim</hi> and <hi>Ochim,</hi> their <hi>habitation</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate? where are thoſe <hi>ancient</hi> people of the lews who were (ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulla micol hagnamim) <hi>his peculiar and choſen people of al na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions?</hi> they are <hi>ſcattered</hi> abroad as a curſe, and their <hi>place</hi> knows them no more. And ſhall I tel you? God hath no <hi>need</hi> of us, he can calthem <hi>Gnammi,</hi> his people, who were <hi>Lo gnammi,</hi> not his
<pb facs="tcp:117534:7"/> people, and them <hi>beloved,</hi> who were not <hi>beloved.</hi> Indeed he hath <hi>held</hi> up us, as if he had not <hi>known</hi> where to have <hi>another</hi> people, if he ſhould <hi>forſake</hi> us we <hi>have</hi> been a <hi>Goſhen,</hi> when others have been an <hi>Egypt,</hi> a <hi>Canaan,</hi> when others an <hi>Akeldama,</hi> the <hi>garden</hi> of God, when others have been a wilderneſſe, our <hi>fleece</hi> hath been <hi>wet,</hi> when others have been <hi>dry:</hi> But <hi>know,</hi> God hath no need of us, he can <hi>want</hi> no people if he <hi>pleaſe</hi> to call; If he ſpeake, <hi>all the ends of the world ſhall remember and turn unto the Lord, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 27, 28. &amp;c. 11 Eſa 9. 10.</note> 
               <hi>all the kindreds of the Nations ſhall worſhip before him.</hi> If he ſet up his <hi>ſtandard, to him ſhal the Gentiles flock,</hi> and <hi>the earth ſhall be full of the knowledge of the Lord, as the waters cover the ſea.</hi> It is not for <hi>need</hi> but for <hi>love</hi> that God abides with <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and there is nothing out of himſelfe the <hi>incentive</hi> of this <note place="margin">Amat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> aliunde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> habet, ſed ip ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> unde an at. Aug.</note> love: there can be no <hi>reaſon</hi> given why <hi>God</hi> ſhould <hi>fence</hi> us, and <hi>ſuffer</hi> other places to lye waſt, that we ſhould bee his <hi>Garden,</hi> and other places a <hi>Wildernes,</hi> that he ſhould <hi>feed</hi> us with the <hi>bread</hi> of Heaven, and <hi>ſuffer</hi> others to <hi>ſtarve,</hi> men of the ſame mould, his <hi>offſpring</hi> as well as we, and ſuch (did he <hi>conquer</hi> to himſelfe) were likely to doe him <hi>more</hi> ſervice, bring him <hi>more</hi> glory then we have done. Wee ſee ſomething here done in order to ſuch a work, our <hi>Harveſt</hi> is much over, we ſee little incomes, there we ſee the <hi>fields are ripe for harveſt;</hi> here the <hi>miniſtry</hi> is contemned, <hi>there the feet of them that bring glad tydings are beautifull;</hi> we have <hi>outlived</hi> the power and efficacy of Ordinances, there God goes ſorth with <hi>life</hi> and power we can <hi>outfit</hi> the moſt ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and <hi>winning diſcoveries</hi> of Chriſt, there every <hi>notion,</hi> breeds <hi>motion</hi> in them; the <hi>glory</hi> of the Lord is much <hi>departed</hi> from us, there his <hi>riſing</hi> is conſpicuous and glorious. The <hi>blind</hi> man found it <hi>good</hi> to be in the <hi>way</hi> where Chriſt came: And who would be in <hi>Aegypt</hi> when there is <hi>light</hi> in <hi>Goſhen?</hi> Oh that <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> would be <hi>quickned</hi> by their riſings, and <hi>weep</hi> ever her own declinings! What a <hi>wonder</hi> is it that they ſhould doe <hi>ſo much,</hi> and we <hi>ſo little,</hi> that they ſhould be <hi>men</hi> in their infancy, and we ſuch <hi>Children</hi> in our <hi>manhood,</hi> that they ſo active, we ſo
<pb facs="tcp:117534:7"/> dead? That which was <hi>Hieroms</hi> complaint may be ours, <hi>O that Infidelity ſhould do that which thoſe who profeſle thenmſelvs</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Healquo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>delu as, quod non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſides. Ignis qui in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s ſuit Cali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lus, in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ucidus.</note> 
               <hi>beleevers cannot do!</hi> We have the <hi>light</hi> of former times, but want the <hi>heat,</hi> knowledge <hi>abounds</hi> as the <hi>waters cover</hi> the ſea, but we <hi>want</hi> the ſalt, we have a <hi>form of Godlineſſe,</hi> but want the <hi>power:</hi> And it wil be <hi>ſmal</hi> comfort ſhould God <hi>continue</hi> to us the form, and <hi>cary</hi> to others the <hi>power,</hi> to ſuffer us to <hi>waſt</hi> our ſelvs with <hi>unneceſſary</hi> brangles (which are the <hi>ſweat</hi> of thetimes) and in the mean to cary the life and <hi>power</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> unto others.</p>
            <p>Let theſe poor <hi>Indians</hi> ſtand up <hi>incentives</hi> to us, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſet up the <hi>Gentiles a provocation</hi> to the Iews: who knows but <note place="margin">Rom. 11. 14.</note> God <hi>gave</hi> life to <hi>New England,</hi> to <hi>quicken Old,</hi> and hath <hi>warmed</hi> them, that they might <hi>heat</hi> us, <hi>raiſed</hi> them from the dead, that they might <hi>recover</hi> us from that conſumption, and thoſe ſad <hi>decayes</hi> which are come upon us?</p>
            <p>This ſmal <hi>Treatiſe</hi> is an <hi>Eſſay</hi> to that end, an <hi>Indian Sermon,</hi> though you will not <hi>hear</hi> us, poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bly when ſome <hi>riſe</hi> from the <hi>dead</hi> you will <hi>hear</hi> them. The main <hi>Doctrin</hi> it preacheth unto all, is to <hi>value</hi> the Goſpel, <hi>prize</hi> the Miniſtry, <hi>loath</hi> not your Manna, ſurfet not of your plenty, be <hi>thankfull</hi> for mercies, <hi>fruitfull</hi> under means: <hi>Awake</hi> from your ſlumber, <hi>repair</hi> your decayes, <hi>redeem</hi> your time, <hi>improve</hi> the ſeaſons of your peace; <hi>anſwer</hi> to cals, <hi>Open</hi> to knocks, <hi>attend</hi> to whiſpers, <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey</hi> commands; you have a <hi>name</hi> you live, take heed you bee not <hi>dead,</hi> you are <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in <hi>ſhew,</hi> be ſo <hi>indeed:</hi> leaſt as you have <hi>loſt</hi> the power, God take away from you the form alſo.</p>
            <p>And you that are <hi>Miniſters</hi> learn by this not to <hi>deſpond</hi> though you ſee not <hi>preſent</hi> fruit of your labors, <hi>though you fiſh all night and catch nothing</hi> God hath a <hi>fulneſſe</hi> of time to <hi>perform</hi> all his purpoſes. And the <hi>deepeſt</hi> degeneracies, <hi>&amp; wideſt</hi> eſtrangements from God, ſhall be no <hi>bar</hi> or obſtacle to the <hi>power</hi> and freeneſſe of his owne grace when that <hi>time</hi> is come.</p>
            <p>And you that are <hi>Merchants,</hi> take <hi>incouragement</hi> from hence to <hi>ſcatter</hi> the becames of light, <hi>to ſpread</hi> and propagate the <hi>Goſpel</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:117534:8"/> into thoſe dark <hi>corners</hi> of the earth; whither you <hi>traffick</hi> you <hi>take much</hi> from them, if you can <hi>carry</hi> this to them, you wil make them an <hi>abundant</hi> recompence. And you that are <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, rejoice to ſee the <hi>Curtaines</hi> of the Tabernacle inlarged, the <hi>bounds</hi> of the Sanctuary <hi>extended, Chriſt</hi> advanced, the <hi>Goſpel</hi> propagated, and <hi>ſouls ſaved.</hi> And if ever the love of God did <hi>center</hi> in your hearts, if ever the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of his goodneſs hath begot <hi>bowels</hi> of compaſſion in you, draw them forth <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> them whom God hath <hi>ſingled</hi> out to be the <hi>objects</hi> of his grace and mercy; lays out your prayers, lend your aſſiſtance to carry on this <hi>day of the Lord</hi> begun among them. They are not able (as <hi>Moſes ſaid) to bear the burthen of that people alone,</hi> to make <hi>proviſion</hi> for the <hi>children</hi> whom God hath given them; &amp; therefore it is requiſite the <hi>ſpiritual community</hi> ſhould help to bear part with them. Many of the <hi>young ones</hi> are given and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in, to be <hi>educated &amp;</hi> brought up in <hi>Schooles,</hi> they are <hi>naked</hi> and muſt be <hi>clad,</hi> they <hi>want</hi> al things, and muſt be <hi>ſupplyed.</hi> The Parents alſo, and many others being convinced of the evill of an <hi>idle life,</hi> deſire to be <hi>employed</hi> in honeſt labor, but they want <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments</hi> and tooles to ſet them on work, and <hi>caſt-garments</hi> to throw upon thoſe bodies, <hi>that their loins may bleſſe you,</hi> whoſe <hi>ſouls</hi> Chriſt hath cloathed. <hi>Soine worthy perſons</hi> have given much; and if God ſhall <hi>move</hi> the heart of others to <hi>offer willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> towards the building of Chriſt a <hi>Spirituall temple,</hi> it will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>remain</hi> upon their account, when the <hi>ſmalleſt rewards</hi> from God, ſhall be better then the greateſt layings out for God. But we are making a relation, not a collection; we leave the whole to your Chriſtian conſideration, not doubting but they who have taſted of mercy from God, will be ready to exerciſe compaſſion to others, &amp; commend you unto him <hi>who gave himſelf for us, that hee</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 9. 14.</note> 
               <hi>might redeem us from all iniquity, and pariſie</hi> as well as pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe <hi>unto himſelf a peculiar people, zealous of good works.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Stephen Marſhall</signed>
               <signed>Ier. Whitaker</signed>
               <signed>Edmund Calamy</signed>
               <signed>William Greenbill</signed>
               <signed>Iohn Downam</signed>
               <signed>Philip Nye</signed>
               <signed>Sy. Simpſan</signed>
               <signed>Williamer Cart.</signed>
               <signed>The Goodwin</signed>
               <signed>The. Caſe</signed>
               <signed>Simeon Aſbe</signed>
               <signed>Samuel B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117534:8"/>
            <head>THE CLEARE SVNSHINE OF THE GOSPELL, Breaking forth upon the INDIANS in <hi>New-England.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Much Honored and deare Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat glorious and ſudden riſing of Chriſt Jeſus upon our poore <hi>Indians</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan a little before you ſet ſaile from theſe ſhores, hath not beene altogether clouded ſince, but rather broken out further into more light and life, wherewith the moſt High hath viſited them; and becauſe ſome may call in queſtion the truth of the firſt relation, either becauſe they may thinke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> too good newes to be true, or becauſe ſome perſons maligning the good of the Countrey, are apt, as to aggravate to the utmoſt any evill thing againſt it, ſo to vilifie and extenuate any good thing in it: and becauſe your ſelfe deſired to heare how ſarre ſince God hath carried on that worke, which your owne eyes ſaw here begun; I ſhall therefore as faithfully and as briefly as I can, give you a true relation of the progreſſe of it, which I hope may be a ſufficient confirmation of what hath been publiſhed to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117534:9"/> the world before, having this as the chieſe end in my owne eye, that the precious Saints and people of God in <hi>England,</hi> beleeving what hath been and may bee reported to them, of theſe things, may help forward this work together with us by their prayers and prayſes, as we deſire to doe the like for the worke of Chriſt begun among them there. I dare not ſpeake too much, nor what I thinke about their converſion, I have ſeen ſo much falſeneſſe in that point among many Engliſh, that I am ſlow to beleeve herein too haſtily concerning theſe poore naked men; onely this is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to all honeſt hearts that dwell neer them, and have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them, that the work of the Lord upon them, and (what ever it bee) is both unexpected and wonderfull in ſo ſhort a time; I ſhall ſet downe things as they are, and then your ſelfe and others to whom theſe may come, may judge as you pleaſe of them.</p>
            <p>Soon after your departure hence, the awakening of theſe <hi>Indiani</hi> in our Towne raiſed a great noyſe among all the reſt round about us, eſpecially about <hi>Concord</hi> ſide where the <note n="*" place="margin">An inferiour Prince.</note> 
               <hi>Sachim</hi> (as I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) and one or two more of his men, hearing of theſe things and of the preaching of the Word, and how it wrought among them here, came therefore hither to <note n="*" place="margin">An Indian town ſo called.</note> 
               <hi>Noonanetum</hi> to the <hi>Indian</hi> Lecture, and what the Lord ſpake to his heart wee know not, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it ſeems hee was ſo farre affected, as that he deſired to become more like to the Engliſh, and to caſt off thoſe <hi>Indian</hi> wild and ſinfull courſes they formerly lived in; but when divers of his men perceived their <hi>Sachims</hi> mind, they ſecretly oppoſed him herein; which oppoſition being known, he therefore called together his chiefe men about him, &amp; made a ſpeech to this effect unto them, <q>
                  <hi>viz</hi> That they had no reaſon at all to oppoſe thoſe courſes the Engliſh were now taking for their good, for (ſaith hee) all the time you have lived after the <hi>Indian</hi> faſhion under the power and protection of higher <hi>Indian Sachems,</hi> what did they care for you? they onely ſought their owne ends out of you, and therefore would exact upon you, and take away your skins and your <hi>Kettles</hi> &amp; your <hi>Wampam</hi> from you at their own pleaſure, &amp; this was al that they regarded: but you may evidently ſee that the Engliſh mind no ſuch things, care for none of your goods, but onely ſeeke your good and welfare, and in ſtead of taking away, are ready to give to you; with many other things I now
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117534:9"/> forget, which were related by an eminent man of that town to me.</q> What the effect of this ſpeech was, we can tell no otherwiſe then as the effects ſhewed it; the firſt thing was, the making of certain Lawes for their more religious and civill government and beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, to the making of which, they craved the aſſiſtance of one of the chiefe <hi>Indians in Noonanetum,</hi> a very active <hi>Indian</hi> to bring in others to the knowledge of God; deſiring withall an able ſaithfull man in <hi>Concord</hi> to record and keep in writing what they had generally agreed upon. Another effect was, their deſire of <note place="margin">Teacher of the Church of <hi>Roxbury,</hi> that preacheth to the <hi>Indians</hi> in their own Language.</note> Mr. <hi>Eliots</hi> coming up to them, to preach, as he could find time among them; and the laſt effect was, their deſire of having a Towne given them within the bounds of <hi>Concord</hi> neare unto the Engliſh. This latter when it was propounded by the <hi>Sachim</hi> of the place, he was demanded why hee deſired a towne ſo neare, when as there was more roome for them up in the Country. To which the <hi>Sachim</hi> replyed, that he therefore deſired it becauſe he knew that if the <hi>Indians</hi> dwelt far from the Engliſh, that they would not ſo much care to pray, nor would they be ſo ready to heare the Word of God, but they would be all one <hi>Indians</hi> ſtill; but dwelling neare the Engliſh he hoped it might bee otherwiſe with them then. The Town therefore was granted them; but it ſeemes that the oppoſition made by ſome of themſelves more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignantly ſet againſt theſe courſes, hath kept them from any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſetling downe: and ſurely this oppoſition is a ſpeciall finger of <hi>Satan</hi> reſiſting theſe budding beginnings; for what more hopefull way of doing them good then by cohabitation in ſuch Townes, neare unto good examples, and ſuch as may be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually whetting upon them, and dropping into them of the things of God? what greater meanes at leaſt to civilize them? as is evident in the <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſco</hi> and <hi>Mexico Indians,</hi> more civill then any elſe in this vaſt Continent that wee know of, who were reduced by the politick principles of the two great conquering Princes of thoſe Countries after their long and tedious wars from theſe wild and wandring courſe of life, unto a ſetling into particular Townes and Cities: but I forebear, only to confirme the truth of theſe things, I have ſent you the orders agreed on at <hi>Concord</hi> by the <hi>Indians,</hi> under the hand of two faithfull witneſſes, who could teſtifie more, if need were, of theſe matters: I have ſent you their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117534:10"/> owne Copy and their own hands to it, which I have here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Concluſions and Orders made and agreed upon by divers Sachims and other principall men amongſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians at</hi> Concord, <hi>in the end of the eleventh moneth, An.</hi> 1646.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. THat every one that ſhall abuſe themſelves with wine or ſtrong liquors, ſhall pay for every time ſo abuſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, 20 <hi>s.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. That there ſhall be no more <hi>Pawwowing</hi> amongſt the <hi>Indians.</hi> And if any ſhall hereafter <note n="*" place="margin">Pawwows are Witches or Sorcere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s that cure by help of the devill,</note> 
                     <hi>Pawwow,</hi> both he that ſhall <hi>Pawwow,</hi> &amp; he that ſhall procure him to <hi>Pawwow,</hi> ſhall pay 20 <hi>s.</hi> apeece.</item>
                  <item>3. They doe deſire that they may be ſtirred up to ſeek after God.</item>
                  <item>4. They deſire they may underſtand the wiles of Satan, and grow out of love with his ſuggeſtions, and temptations.</item>
                  <item>5. That they may fall upon ſome better courſe to improve their time, then formerly.</item>
                  <item>6. That they may be brought to the ſight of the ſinne of lying, and whoſever ſhall be found faulty herein ſhall pay for the firſt offence 5 <hi>s.</hi> the ſecond 10 <hi>s.</hi> the third 20 <hi>s.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7. Whoſoever ſhall ſteale any thing from another, ſhall reſtore fourfold.</item>
                  <item>8. They deſire that no <hi>Indian</hi> hereafter ſhall have any more but one wife.</item>
                  <item>9. They deſire to prevent falling out of <hi>Indians</hi> one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that they may live quietly one by another.</item>
                  <item>10. That they may labour after humility, and not be proud.</item>
                  <item>11. That when <hi>Indians</hi> doe wrong one to another, they may be lyable to cenſure by <hi>fine</hi> or the like, as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are.</item>
                  <item>12. That they pay their debts to the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>13. That they doe obſerve the Lords-Day, and whoſoever ſhall prophane it ſhall pay 20 <hi>s.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>14. That there ſhall not be allowance to <hi>pick</hi> Lice, as formerly, and eate them, and whoſoever ſhall offend in this caſe ſhall pay for every louſe a penny.</item>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:117534:10"/>
                  <item>15. They will weare their <hi>haire</hi> comely, as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> do, and whoſoever ſhall offend here in ſhall pay 5 <hi>s.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>16. They intend to reforme themſelves, in their former greaſing themſelves, under the Penalty of 5 <hi>s.</hi> for every default.</item>
                  <item>17. They doe all reſolve to ſet up prayer in their <hi>wigwams,</hi> and to <note place="margin">A Wigwam is ſuch a dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling houſe as they live in.</note> 
                     <hi>ſeek</hi> to God both before and after meate.</item>
                  <item>18. If any committhe ſinne of fornication, being ſingle perſons, the man ſhall pay 20 <hi>s.</hi> and the woman 10 <hi>s.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>19. If any man lie with a breaſt he ſhall die.</item>
                  <item>20. Whoſoever ſhall play at their former games ſhall pay 10 <hi>s.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>21. Whoſoever ſhall commit adultery ſhall be put to death.</item>
                  <item>22. Wilfull Murder ſhall be puniſhed with death.</item>
                  <item>23. They ſhall not diſguiſe themſelves in their mournings, as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly; nor ſhall they keep a great noyſe by howling.</item>
                  <item>24. The old Ceremony of the Maide walking alone and living apart ſo many dayes 20 <hi>s.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>25. No <hi>Indian</hi> ſhall take an Engliſh mans <note n="*" place="margin">A Canooe is a ſmall Boate.</note> 
                     <hi>Canooe</hi> without leave under the penaltie of 5 <hi>s.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>26. No <hi>Indian</hi> ſhall come into any <hi>Engliſh</hi> mans houſe except he firſt knock: and this they expect from the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>27. Whoſoever beats his wife ſhall pay 20 <hi>s.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>28. If any <hi>Indian</hi> ſhall fall out with, and beate another <hi>Indian,</hi> he ſhall pay 20 <hi>s.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>29. They deſire they may bee a towne, and either to dwell on this ſide the <hi>Beare Swamp,</hi> or at the Eaſt ſide of Mr. <hi>Flints Pond.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Immediatly after theſe things were agreed upon, moſt of the <hi>Indians</hi> of theſe parts, ſet up Prayer morning and evening in their families, and before and after meat. They alſo generally cut their haire, and were more civill in their carriage to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> then formerly. And they doe manifeſt a great willingneſſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form themſelves to the civill faſhions of the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> The Lords day they keepe a day of reſt, and miniſter what edification they can to one another. Theſe former orders were put into this forme by Captaine <hi>Simond Willard</hi> of <hi>Concord,</hi> whom the <hi>Indians</hi> with unanimous conſent intreated to bee their Recorder, being very ſolicitous that what they did agree upon might be faithfully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved without alteration.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Thomas Flint.</signed>
                  <signed>Simon Willard.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:117534:11"/>
               <p>Theſe things thus wrought in a ſhort time about <hi>Concord</hi> ſide, I looke upon as fruits of the miniſtery of the Word; for although their high eſteem bred lately in them, eſpecially the chief and beſt of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> together with that mean eſteem many of them have of themſelves, and therefore will call themſelves ſometimes <hi>poore Creatures,</hi> when they ſee and heare of their great diſtance from others of the Engliſh; I ſay, although theſe things may be ſome cauſes of making theſe orders and walking in theſe courſes, yet the chiefe cauſe ſeemes to bee the power of the Word, which hath been the chiefe cauſe of theſe Orders, and therefore it is that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till now of late they never ſo much as thought of any of theſe things.</p>
               <p>I am not able to acquaint you very much from my owne eye and care witneſſe of things, for you know the neare relation between me and the fire ſide uſually all winter time, onely I ſhall impart two or three things more of what I have heard and ſeen, and the reſt I ſhall relate to you as I have received from faithfull witneſſes, who teſtifie nothing to me by their writings, but what is ſeene in the open Sun, and done in the view of all the world, and generally known to be true of people abiding in theſe parts wee live in.</p>
               <p>As ſoone as ever the fierceneſſe of the winter was paſt, March. 3. 1647. I went out to <hi>Noonanetum</hi> to the <hi>Indian</hi> Lecture, where Mr. <hi>Willſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Alleu,</hi> of <hi>Dedham,</hi> Mr. <hi>Dunſter,</hi> beſide many otherChriſtains were preſent; on which day perceiving divers of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> women well affected, and conſidering that their ſoules might ſtand in need of anſwer to their ſcruples as well as the mens; &amp; yet becauſe we knew how unfit it was for women ſo much as to aske queſtions publiquely immediatly by themſelves; wee did therefore deſire them to propound any queſtions they would bee reſolved about by firſt acquainting either their Husbands, or the Interpreter privately therewith: whereupon we heard two que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions thus orderly propounded; which becauſe they are the firſt that ever were propounded by <hi>Indian</hi> women in ſuch an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance that ever wee heard of, and becauſe they may bee other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe uſefull, I ſhall therefore ſet them downe.</p>
               <p>The firſt queſtion was propounded by the wiſe of one <hi>Wampooas</hi> a well affected <hi>Indian, viz.</hi> 
                  <q>whether (ſaid ſhe) do I pray when
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117534:11"/> my husband prayes if I ſpeak nothing as he doth, yet if I like what he ſaith, and my heart goes with it?</q> (for the <hi>Indians</hi> will many times pray with their wives, and with their children alſo ſometime in the fields) ſhee therefore ſearing leſt prayer ſhould onely be an externall action of the lips, enquired if it might not be alſo an inward action of the heart, if ſhe liked of what he ſaid.</p>
               <p>The ſecond queſtion was propounded by the Wiſe of one <hi>Tother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwampe,</hi> her meaning in her queſtion (as wee all perceived) was this, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>Whether a husband ſhould do well to pray with his wife, and yet continue in his paſſions; &amp; be angry with his wife?</q> But the modeſty and wiſdome of the woman directed her to doe three things in one, ſor thus ſhee ſpake to us, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>Before my husband did pray hee was much angry and froward, but ſince hee hath begun to pray hee was not angry ſo much, but little angry:</q> wherein firſt ſhee gave an honorable teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of her husband and commended him for the abatement of his paſſion; ſecondly, ſhee gave implicitly a ſecret reproofe for what was paſt, and for ſomewhat at preſent that was amiſſe; and thirdly, it was intended by her as a queſtion whether her husband ſhould pray to God, and yet continue in ſome unruly paſſions; but ſhe wifely avoyded that, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt it might reflect too much upon him, although wee deſired her to expreſſe if that was not her meaning.</p>
               <p>At this time (beſide theſe queſtions) there were ſundry others propounded of very good uſe, in all which we ſaw the Lord Jeſus leading them to make narrow inquiries into the things of God, that ſo they might ſee the reality of them. I have heard few Chriſtians when they begin to looke toward God, make more ſearching queſtions that they might ſee things really, and not onely have a notion of them: I for beare to mention any of them, becauſe I forget the chiefe of them; onely this wee tooke notice of at this dayes meeting, that there was an aged <hi>Indian</hi> who propoſed his complaint in propounding his queſtion concerning an unruly diſobedient ſon, and "what one ſhould do with him "in caſe of obſtinacy and diſobedience, and that will not heare "Gods Word, though his Father command him, nor will not "forſake his drunkenneſſe, though his father forbid him? Unto which there were many anſwers to ſet forth the ſinne of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117534:12"/> to parents; which were the more quickned and ſharpned becauſe wee knew that this rebellious ſonne whom the old man meant, was by Gods providence preſent at this Lecture: Mr. <hi>Wilſon</hi> was much inlarged, and ſpake ſo terribly, yet ſo graciouſly as might have affected a heart not quite ſhut up, which this young <hi>deſperado</hi> hearing (who well underſtood the <hi>Engliſh</hi> tongue) inſtead of humbling himſelf before the Lords Word, which touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his conſcience and condition ſo neare, hee was filled with a ſpirit of Satan, and as ſoone as ever Mr. <hi>Wilſons</hi> ſpeech was ended hee brake out into a loud contemptucus expreſſion; <hi>So,</hi> ſaith he: which we paſſed by without ſpeaking againe, leaving the Word with him, which we knew would one day take its effect one way or other upon him.</p>
               <p>The latter end of this yeare Mr. <hi>Wilſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Eliot,</hi> and my ſelfe were ſent for by thoſe in <hi>Tarmoutb</hi> to meet with ſome other El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Plimoutb pattent,</hi> to heare and heale (if it were the will of Chriſt) the difference and ſad breaches which have been too long a time among them, wherein the Lord was very mercifull to us and them in binding them up beyond our thoughts in a very ſhort time, in giving not only that bruiſed Church but the whole Towne alſo a hopefull beginning of ſetled peace and future quietneſſe; but Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> as hee takes all other advantages of time, ſo hee tooke this, of ſpeaking with, and preaching to the poore <hi>Indians</hi> in theſe remote places about <hi>Cape Cod:</hi> in which journey I ſhall acquaint you with what all of us obſerved.</p>
               <p>Wee firſt found theſe <hi>Indians</hi> (not very farre from ours) to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand (but with much difficulty) the uſuall language of thoſe in our parts, partly in regard of the different dialect which ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally varies in 40. or 60. miles, and partly and eſpecially in regard of their not being accuſtomed unto ſacred language about the holy things of God, wherein Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> excells any other of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that in the <hi>Indian</hi> language about common matters excell him: I ſay therefore although they did with much diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty underſtand him, yet they did underſtand him, although by many circumlocutions and variations of ſpeech and the helpe of one or two Interpreters which were then preſent.</p>
               <p>Secondly, wee obſerved much oppoſition againſt him, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of him at the day appointed, eſpecially by one of the chiefeſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117534:12"/> 
                  <hi>Sacbims</hi> in thoſe parts, a man of a fierce, ſtrong and ſurious ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit whom the <hi>Engliſh</hi> therefore call by the name <hi>John:</hi> who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though before the day appointed for preaching, promiſed very faire that he would come and bring his men with him; yet that very morning when they were to bee preſent, he ſends out almoſt all his men to Sea, pretending fiſhing, and therefore although at laſt he came late himſelfe to the Sermon, yet his men were ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and when he came himſelf, would not ſeem to underſtand any thing, although hee did underſtand as ſome of the <hi>Indians</hi> themſelves then told us, when Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> by himſelf and by them inquired of him if he underſtood what was ſpoken: yet he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued hearing what was ſaid with a dogged looke and a diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented countenance.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, not withſtanding this oppoſition wee found another <hi>Sachim</hi> then preſent willing to learne, and divers of his men at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive and knowing what was ſaid: and in the time which is uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſet apart for propounding queſtions, an aged <hi>Indian</hi> told us openly, <q>That theſe very things which Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> had taugh: them as the Commandements of God, and concerning God, and the making of the world by one God, that they had heard ſome old men who were now dead, to ſay the ſame things, ſince whoſe death there hath been no remembrance or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of them among the <hi>Indians</hi> untill now they heare of them againe.</q> Which when I heard ſolemnly ſpoken, I could not tell how thoſe old <hi>Indians</hi> ſhould attaine to ſuch knowledge, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe perhaps by means of the <hi>French</hi> Preacher caſt upon thoſe coaſts many yeers ſince, by whoſe miniſtry they might poſſibly reape and retaine ſome knowledge of thoſe things; this alſo I hear by a godly and able Chriſtain who hath much converſe with them; that many of them have this apprehenſion now ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring among them, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>That their forefathers did know God, but that after this, they ſell into a great ſleep, and when they did awaken they quite forgot him,</q> (for under ſuch metaphori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call language they uſually expreſſe what eminent things they meane:) ſo that it may ſeeme to be the day of the Lords gracious viſitation of theſe poore Natives, which is juſt as it is with all other people, when they are moſt low, the wheele then turnes, and the Lord remembers to have mercy.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:117534:13"/>
               <p>Fourthly, a fourth and laſt obſervation wee took, was the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of an <hi>Indian</hi> in thoſe parts, telling us of his dreame many yeers ſince, which he told us of openly before many witneſſes when we ſate at meat: the dreame is this, hee ſaid <q>That about two yeers before the <hi>Engliſh</hi> came over into thoſe parts there was a great mortality among the <hi>Indians,</hi> and one night he could not ſleep above half the night, after which hee fell into a dream, in which he did think he ſaw a great many men come to thoſe parts in cloths, juſt as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> now are apparelled, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them there a roſe up a man all in black, with a thing in his hand which hee now ſees was all one <hi>Engliſh</hi> mans book; this black man he ſaid ſtood upon a higher place then all the reſt, and on the one ſide of him were the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> on the other a great number of <hi>Indians:</hi> this man told all the <hi>Indians</hi> that God was <hi>mooſquantum</hi> or angry with them, and that he would kill them for their ſinnes, whereupon he ſaid himſelf ſtood up, and deſired to know of the black man what God would do with him and his <hi>Squaw</hi> and <hi>Papooſes</hi> but the black man would not anſwer him a firſt time, nor yet a ſecond time, untill he deſired the third time, and then he ſmil'd upon him, and told him that he and his <hi>Papooſes</hi> ſhould be ſafe, and that God would give unto them <hi>Mitcheu, (i. e.)</hi> victualls and other good things, and ſo hee awakened.</q> What ſimilitude this dream hath with the truth accompliſhed, you may eaſily ſee. I attribute little to dreams, yet God may ſpeak to ſuch by them rather then to thoſe who have a more ſure Word to direct and warn them, yet this dream made us think ſurely this <hi>Indian</hi> will regard the black man now come among them rather then any others of them: but whether Satan, or fear, and guilt, or world prevailed, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay, but this is certaine, that he withdrew from the Sermon, and although hee came at the latter end of it, as hoping it had been done, yet we could not perſwade him then to ſtay and hear, but away he flung, and we ſaw him no more till next day.</p>
               <p>From this third of <hi>March</hi> untill the latter end of this Summer I could not be preſent at the <hi>Indian</hi> Lectures, but when I came this laſt time, I marvailed to ſee ſo many <hi>Indian</hi> men, women and children in <hi>Engliſh</hi> apparell, they being at <hi>Noonan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tum</hi> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally clad, eſpecially upon Lecture dayes, which they have got
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117534:13"/> partly by gift from the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and partly by their own labours, by which ſome of them have very handſomely apparelled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, &amp; you would ſcare know them from <hi>Engliſh</hi> people. There is one thing more which I would acquaint you with, which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this Summer, <hi>viz. June 9.</hi> the firſt day of the Synods meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> where the forenoon was ſpent in hearing a Sermon preached by one of the <hi>Elders</hi> as a preparative to the worke of the Synod, the afternoon was ſpent in hearing an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> Lecture where there was a great confluence of <hi>Indians</hi> all parts to heare Mr. <hi>Eliot,</hi> which we conceived not unſeaſonable at ſuch a time, partly that the reports of Gods worke begun among them, might be ſeen and beleeved of the chief who were then ſent and met from all the Churches of Chriſt in the Countrey, who could hardly beleeve the reports they had received concerning theſe new ſtirs among the <hi>Indians,</hi> and partly hereby to raiſe up a greater ſpirit of prayer for the carrying on of the work begun upon the <hi>Indians,</hi> among all the Churches and ſervants of the Lord Jeſus: The Sermon was ſpent in ſhewing them their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable condition without Chriſt, out of <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 1. that they were dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes, and in pointing unto them the Lord Jeſus, who onely could quicken them.</p>
               <p>When the Sermon was done, there was a convenient ſpace of time ſpent in hearing thoſe queſtions which the <hi>Indians</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely propounded, and in giving anſwers to them; one queſtion was, <hi>What Countrey man Chriſt was, and where he was borne?</hi> Another was, <hi>How farre off that place was from us here?</hi> Another was, <hi>Where Chriſt now was?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And another, <hi>How they might lay hold on him, and where, being now abſent from them?</hi> with ſome other to this purpoſe; which received full anſwers from ſeverall hands. But that which I note is this, that their gracious attention to the Word, the affections and mournings of ſome of them under it, their ſober propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of divers ſpirituall queſtions, their aptneſſe to underſtand and beleeve what was replyed to them, the readlineſſe of divers poore naked children to anſwer openly the chief queſtions in Catechiſm which were formerly taught them, and ſuch like ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances of a great change upon them, did marvellouſly affect all the wiſe and godly Miniſters, Magiſtrates, &amp; people, and did
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117534:14"/> raiſe their hearts up to great thankfulneſſe to God; very many deeply and abundantly mourning for joy to ſee ſuch a bleſſed day, and the Lord Jeſus ſo much known and ſpoken of among ſuch as never heard of him before: So that if any in <hi>England</hi> doubt of the truth of what was formerly w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it, or if any malignant eye ſhall queſtion and v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>e this work, they will now ſpeak too late, for what was here done at <hi>Cambridge</hi> was not ſet under a Buſhell, but in the open Sunne, that what <hi>Thomas</hi> would not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve by the reports of others, he might be forced to beleeve, by ſeeing with his own eyes and feeling Chriſt Jeſus thus riſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them with his own hands.</p>
               <p>I have done with what I have obſerved my ſelf; I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore proceed to give you a true relation of what I have heard from others, and many faithfull witneſſes have ſeene: and firſt I ſhall ſpeake a little more of the old man who is mentioned in the ſtory now in print; this old man hath much affection ſtirred up. by the Word, and comming to Mr. <hi>Eliots</hi> houſe (for of him I had this ſtory) Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> told him that becauſe he brought his wife &amp; all his children conſtantly to the Lecture, that he would there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beſtow ſome Cloths upon him, (it being now winter &amp; the old man naked:) which promiſe he not certainly underſtanding the meaning of, asked therefore of another <hi>Indian</hi> (who is Mr. <hi>Eliots</hi> ſervant and very hopefull) what it was that Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed him? he told him that hee ſaid hee would give him ſome Cloths; which when hee underſtood, hee affectionately brake out into theſe expreſſions, <hi>God I ſee is mercifull:</hi> a bleſſed, becauſe a plain hearted affectionate ſpeech, and worthy <hi>Engliſh</hi> mens thoughts when they put on their Cloths; to thinke that a poor blind <hi>Indian</hi> that ſcarce ever heard of God before, that he ſhould ſee not only God in his Cloths, but mercy alſo in a promiſe of a caſt off worne ſute of Cloths, which were then given him, and which now he daily weares. But to proceed;</p>
               <p>This ſame old man (as I think a little before hee had theſe Cloths) after an <hi>Indian</hi> Lecture, when they uſually come to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound queſtions; inſtead of asking a queſtion, began to ſpeak to the reſt of the <hi>Indians,</hi> and brake out into many expreſſions of wond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing at Gods goodneſſe unto them, that the Lord ſhould at laſt look upon them and ſend his Word as a light unto them
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117534:14"/> that had been in darkneſſe and ſuch groſſe ignorance ſo long; me wonder (ſaith he) at God that he ſhould thus deale with us. This ſpeech expreſſed in many words in the <hi>Indian</hi> Languages, and with ſtrong actings of his eyes and hands, being interpreted after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> did much alſo affect all of them that were preſent this Lecture alſo.</p>
               <p>There were this winter many other queſtions propounded, which were writ down by Mr. <hi>Edward Jackſon</hi> one of our Town, conſtantly preſent at theſe Lectures, to take notes both of the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions made by the <hi>Indians</hi> and returned by Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> to them; this man having ſent me in his notes, I ſhall ſend you a taſt of ſome of them.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Why ſome men were ſo bad, that they hate thoſe men that would teach them good things?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Whether the devill or man were made firſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Whether if a father prayes to God to teach his ſons to know him, and he doth teach them himſelf and they will not learn to know God, what ſhould ſuch fathers doe?</hi> (this was propounded by an old man that had rude children.)</p>
               <p n="4">4 A <note n="*" place="margin">Indian wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</note> 
                  <hi>Squaw</hi> propounded this queſtion, <hi>Whether ſhe might not go &amp; pray in ſome private place in the woods, when her husband was not at home, becauſe ſhe was aſhamed to pray in the Wigwam before company?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 <hi>How may one know wicked men, who are good and who are bad?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6 <hi>To what Nation Jeſus Chriſt came firſt unto, and when?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7 <hi>If a man ſhould be incloſed in Iron a foot thick and thrown into the fire, what would become of his ſoule, whether could the ſoule come forth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ce or not?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8 <hi>Why did not God give all men good hearts that they might bee good?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9 <hi>If one ſhould be taken among ſtrange Indians that know not God, and they would make him to fight againſt ſome that he ſhould not and be refuſe, and for his refuſall they kill him, what would become of his ſoule in ſuch a caſe?</hi> This was propounded by a <note n="*" place="margin">They hold that their ſtout and vali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> men have a reward after death.</note> ſtout fellow who was affected.</p>
               <p n="10">10 <hi>How long it is before men beleeve that have the Word of God made known to them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11 <hi>How they ſhould know when their faith is good, and their prayers good prayers?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:117534:15"/>12 <hi>Why did not God kill the Devill that made all men ſo bad, God having all power?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13 <hi>If we be made weak by ſinne in our hearts, how can we come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God to ſanctifie a Sabbath?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There were many more queſtions of this kind, as alſo many Philoſophicall about the Sunne, Moon, Stats, Earth and Seas, Thunder, Lightning, Earthquakes, &amp;c. which I forbear to make mention of, leſt I ſhould clog your time with reading, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the various anſwers to them: by theſe you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in what ſtreame their minds are carried, and that the Lord Jeſus hath at laſt an enquiring people among theſe poor naked men, that formerly never ſo much as thought of him; which queſtionings and enquiries are accounted of by ſome as part of the whitenings of the harveſt toward, wherever they are found among any people, the good and benefit that comes to them hereby is and will be exceeding great.</p>
               <p>We had this year a malignant drunken <hi>Indian,</hi> that (to caſt ſome reproach, as wee feared, upon this way) boldly propounded this queſtion, Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>Who made Sack? who made Sack?</hi> but he was ſoon ſnib'd by the other <hi>Indians,</hi> calling it <note n="*" place="margin">That is a childiſh queſtion.</note> a <hi>Papooſe</hi> queſtion, and ſeriouſly and gravely anſwered (not ſo much to his queſtion, as to his ſpirit) by Mr. <hi>Eliot,</hi> which hath cooled his boldneſſe ever ſince, while others have gone on comfortably in this profitable and pleaſant way.</p>
               <p>The man who ſent me theſe and the like queſtions with their ſeverall anſwers in writing, concluded his letter with this ſtory, which I ſhall here inſert, that you may ſee the more of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong theſe poore people:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Upon the 25. of <hi>Aprill</hi> laſt (ſaith he) I had ſome occaſion to go to ſpeack with <note n="*" place="margin">An Indian S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>m.</note> 
                     <hi>Wabun</hi> about Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing in the morning, and ſtaying ſome half an hours time, as I came back by one of the <hi>Wigwams,</hi> the man of that <hi>Wig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wam</hi> was at prayer; at which I was ſo much affected, that I could not but ſtand under a Tree within hearing, though I could not underſtand but little of his words, and conſider that God was fulfilling his Word, <hi>viz. The ends of the earth ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>member themſelves and turne unto him;</hi> and that Scripture, <hi>Thou art <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> God that heareſt pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er, unto thee ſhall all fleſh come.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Alſo this preſent <hi>September</hi> I have obſerved one of them to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117534:15"/> call his children to him from their gathering of Corne in the field, and to crave a bleſſing, with much affection, having but a homely dinner to eate.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Theſe things me thinkes ſhould move bowels, and awaken <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> hearts to be thankfull, it is no ſmall part of Religion to awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with God in family prayer, (as it ſeems theſe doe it early) and to crave a bleſſing with affectionate hearts upon a homely dinner, perhaps parcht Corne or <hi>Indian</hi> ſtalks: I wiſh the like hearts and wayes were ſeen in many <hi>Engliſh</hi> who profeſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Chriſtians, and that herein and many the like excellencies they were become <hi>Indians,</hi> excepting that name, as he did in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſe, except his bonds: and that you may ſee not only how farre Religion, but civility hath taken place among them, you may be pleaſed therefore to peruſe this Court Order, which is here inſerted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Order made laſt Generall Court at</hi> Boſton <hi>the 26. of</hi> May, 1647. <hi>concerning the</hi> Indians, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>VPon information that the <hi>Indians</hi> dwelling among us, and ſubmitted to our government, being by the Miniſtry of the Word brought to ſome civility, are deſirous to have a courſe of ordinary Judicature ſet up among them: It is therefore or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by authority of this Court, that ſome one or more of the Magiſtrates, as they ſhall agree amongſt themſelves, ſhall once every quarter keep a Court at ſuch place, where the <hi>Indians</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily aſſemble to hear the Word of God, and may then hear and determine all cauſes both civill and criminall, not being ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall, concerning the <hi>Indians</hi> only, and that the <hi>Indian Sachims</hi>ſhall have libertie to take order in the nature of Summons or At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachments, to bring any of their own people to the ſaid Courts, and to keep a Court of themſelves, every moneth if they ſee occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to determine ſmall cauſes of a civill nature, and ſuch ſmaller criminall cauſes, as the ſaid Magiſtrates ſhall referre to them; and the ſaid <hi>Sachims</hi> ſhall appoint Officers to ſerve Warrante, and to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117534:16"/> execute the Orders and Judgements of either of the ſaid Courts, which Officers ſhall from time to time bee allowed by the ſaid Magiſtrates in the quarter Courts or by the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: And that all ſines to bee impoſed upon any <hi>Indian</hi> in any of the ſaid Courts, ſhall goe and bee beſtowed towards the building of ſome meeting houſes, for education of their poorer children in learning, or other publick uſe, by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the ſaid Magiſtrates and of Maſter <hi>Eliot,</hi> or of ſuch other Elder, as ſhall ordinarily inſtruct them in the true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And it is the deſire of this Court, that theſe Magiſtrates and Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> or ſuch other Elders as ſhall attend the keeping of the ſaid Courts will carefully indeavour to make the Indians under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand our moſt uſefull Lawes, and the principles of reaſon, juſtice and equity whereupon they are grounded, &amp; it is deſired that ſome care may be taken of the <hi>Indians</hi> on the Lords dayes.</p>
               <p>Thus having had a deſire to acquaint you with theſe procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings among the <hi>Indians,</hi> and being deſirous that you might more fully underſtand, eſpecially from him who is beſt able to judge, I did therefore intreat my brother <hi>Eliot</hi> after ſome confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence about theſe things, to ſet down under his own hand what he hath obſerved lately among them: which I do therefore herein ſend unto you in his owne hand writing as he ſent it unto mee, which I think is worthy all Chriſtian thankfull eares to heare, and wherein they may ſee a little of the Spirit of this man of God, whom in other reſpects, but eſpecially for his unwearied<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in this work of God, going up and down among them and doing them good, I think we can never love nor honour enough.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Letter of</hi> Mr. Eliot <hi>to</hi> T. S. <hi>concerning the late work of God among the</hi> Indians.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Deare Brother,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>AT your deſire I have wrote a few things touching the <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> which at preſent came to my mind, as being ſome of thoſe paſſages which took principall impreſſion in my heart,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117534:16"/> wherein I thought I ſaw the Lord, and ſaid the finger of God is here.</p>
               <p>That which I firſt aymed at was to declare &amp; deliver unto them the Law of God, to civilize them, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> courſe the Lord took by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> to give the Law to that rude company becauſe of tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 19. to convince, bridle, reſtrain, and civilize them, and alſo to humble them. But when I firſt attempted it, they gave no heed unto it, but were weary, and rather deſpiſed what I ſaid. A while after God ſtirred up in ſome of them a deſire to come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> faſhions, and live after their manner, but knew not how to attain unto it, yea deſpaired that ever it ſhould come to paſſe in their dayes, but thought that in 40. yeers more, ſome <hi>Indians</hi> would be all one <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and in an hundred yeers, all <hi>Indians</hi> here about, would ſo bee: which when I heard, (for ſome of them told me they thought ſo, and that ſome wiſe <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> ſaid ſo) my heart moved within mee, abhorring that wee ſhould ſit ſtill and let that work alone, and hoping that this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in them was of the Lord, and that this mind in them was a preparative to imbrace the Law and Word of God; and therefore I told them that they and wee were already all one ſave in two things, which make the only difference betwixt them and us: Firſt, we know, ſerve, and pray unto God, and they doe not: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, we labour and work in building, planting, clothing our ſelves, &amp;c. and they doe not: and would hey but doe as wee doe in theſe things, they would be all one with <hi>Engliſh</hi> men: they ſaid they did not know God, and therefore could not tell how to pray to him, nor ſerve him. I told them if they would learn to know God, I would teach them: unto which they being very willing, I then taught them (as I ſundry times had indeavored aſore) but never found them ſo forward, attentive and deſirous to learn till this time, and then I told them I would come to their <hi>Wig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wams,</hi> and teach them, their wives and children, which they ſeemed very glad of; and from that day forward I have not fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to doe that poore little which you know I doe.</p>
               <p>I firſt began with the <hi>Indians</hi> of <hi>Noonanetum,</hi> as you know, thoſe of <hi>Dorcheſter mill</hi> not regarding any ſuch thing: but the better ſort of them perceiving how acceptable this was to the Engliſh, both to Magiſtrates, and all the good people, it pleaſed God to ſtep in and bow their hearts to deſire to be taught to know God,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117534:17"/> and pray unto him likewiſe, and had not I gone unto them alſo, and taught them when I did, they had prevented me, and deſired me ſo to do, as I afterward heard.</p>
               <p>The effect of the Word which appears among them, and the change that is among them is this: Firſt, they have utterly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken all their <hi>Powwaws,</hi> and given over that diabolicall exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, being convicted that it is quite contrary to praying unto God; yea ſundry of their <hi>Powwaws</hi> have renounced their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked imployment, have condemned it as evill, and reſolved ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to uſe it anymore; others of them, ſeeing their imployment and gaines were utterly gone here, have fled to other places, where they are ſtill entertained, and have raiſed lies, ſlanders, and an evill report upon thoſe that heare the Word, and pray unto God, and alſo upon the Engliſh that indeavour to reclaime them and inſtruct them, that ſo they might diſcourage others from praying unto God, for that they account as a principall ſigne of a good man, and call all religion by that name, praying to God; and beſide they mock and ſcoffe at thoſe <hi>Indians</hi> which pray, and blaſpheme God when they pray; as this is one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. A ſober <hi>Indian</hi> going up into the countrey with two of hisſons, did pray (as his manner was at home) and talked to them of God and Jeſus Chriſt: but they mocked, &amp; called one of his ſons <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and the other <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> ſo that they are not without oppoſition raiſed by the <hi>Pawwaws,</hi> and other wicked <hi>Indians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe as they have forſaken their former Religion, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of worſhip, ſo they doe pray unto God conſtantly in their families, morning and evening, and that with great affection, as hath been ſeen and heard by ſundry that have gone to their <hi>Wigwams</hi> at ſuch times; as alſo when they goe to meat they ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly pray and give thanks to God, as they ſee the Engliſh to doe: ſo that that curſe which God threatens to poure out upon the families that call not on his name, is through his grace, and tender mercy ſtayed from breaking forth againſt them, and when they come to Engliſh houſes, they deſire to be taught; and if meat bee given them, they pray and give thanks to God: and uſually expreſſe their great joy, that they are taught to know God, and their great affection to them that teach them.</p>
               <p>Further more they are carefull to inſtruct their children, that ſo when I come they might be ready to anſwer their Catechize,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117534:17"/> which by the often repeating of it to the children, the men and women can readily anſwer to.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe they are carefull to ſanctifie the Sabbath, but at firſt they could not tell how to doe it, and they asked of mee how they ſhould doe it, propounding it as a queſtion whether they ſhould come to the Engliſh meetings or meet among themſelves; they ſaid, if they come to the Engliſh meetings they underſtand nothing, or to no purpoſe, and if they met together among themſelves, they had none that could teach them. I told them that it was not pleaſing to God, nor profitable to themſelves, to hear and underſtand nothing, nor having any that could inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret to them. Therefore I counſelled them to meet together, and deſire thoſe that were the wiſeſt and beſt men to pray, and then to teach the reſt ſuch things as I had taught them from Gods Word, as well as they could; and when one hath done, then let another do the like, and then a third, and when that was done aske me, &amp;c. and to pray unto God to help them therein: and this is the manner how they ſpend their Sabbaths.</p>
               <p>They are alſo ſtrict againſt any prophanation of the Sabbath, by working, fiſhing, hunting, &amp;c. and have a Law to puniſh ſuch as are delinquents therein by a fine of 10 s. and ſundry caſes they have had, wherein they have very ſtrictly proſecuted ſuch as have any way prophaned the Sabbath. As for example, upon a Sabbath morning <hi>Cutchamaquin</hi> the <hi>Sachim</hi> his wife going to fetch water met with other women, and ſhe began to talk of wordly matters, and ſo held on their diſcourſe a while, which evill came to <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hantons</hi> eare, who was to teach that day (this <hi>Nabanton</hi> is a ſober good man, and a true friend to the Engliſh ever ſince our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming) ſo he bent his diſcourſe to ſhew the ſanctification of the Sabbath, &amp; reproved ſuch evils as did violate the ſame; &amp; among other things wordly talk, and thereupon reproved that which he heard of that morning. After hee had done, they fell to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe about it, and ſpent much time therein, hee ſtanding to prove that it was a ſinne, and ſhe doubting of it, ſeeing it was early in the morning, and in private; and alledging that he was more to blame then ſhe, becauſe he had occaſioned ſo much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in the publick meeting: but in concluſion they determined
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117534:18"/> to refer the caſe to me, and accordingly they did come to my houſe on the ſecond day morning and opened all the matter, and I gave them ſuch direction as the Lord directed me unto, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his holy Word.</p>
               <p>Another caſe was this, upon a Lords day towards night two ſtrangers came to <hi>Wabans Wigwam</hi> (it being uſuall with them to travaile on that day, as on any other; (and when they came in, they told him that at a place about a mile off they had chaſed a <hi>Rackoone,</hi> and he betook himſelf into an hollow tree, and if they would goe with them, they might fell the tree and take him: at which tidings, <hi>Waban</hi> being willing to be ſo well provide to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain thoſe ſtrangers (a common practiſe among them, freely to entertain travailers and ſtrangers) he ſent his two ſervants with them, who felled the tree, and took the beaſt. But this act of his was an offence to the reſt, who judged it a violation of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, and moved agitation among them: but the concluſion was, it was to bee moved as a queſtion upon the next Lecture day; which was accordingly done, and received ſuch anſwer as the Lord guided unto by his Word.</p>
               <p>Another caſe was this, upon a Lords day their publick meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting holding long, and ſomewhat what late, when they came at home, in one <hi>Wigwam</hi> the fire was almoſt out, and therefore the man of the houſe, as he ſate by the fire ſide took his Hatchet and ſplit a little dry peece of wood, which they reſerve on purpoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for ſuch uſe, and ſo kindled his fire, which being taken notice of, it was thought to bee ſuch a worke as might not lawfully be done upon the Sabbath day, and therefore the caſe was propounded the Lecture following for their better information.</p>
               <p>Theſe inſtances may ſerve to ſhew their care of the externall obſervation of the Sabbath day.</p>
               <p>In my exerciſe among them (as you know) wee attend foure things, beſides prayer unto God, for his preſence and bleſſing upon all we doe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I catechize the children and youth; wherein ſome are very ready &amp; expert, they can readily ſay all the Commandements, ſo far as I have communicated them, and all other principles about the creation, the fall, the redemption by Chriſt, &amp;c. wherein alſo the aged people are pretty expert, by the frequent repetition
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117534:18"/> thereof to the children, and are able to teach it to their children at home, and do ſo.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I Preach unto them out of ſome texts of Scripture, wherein I ſtudy all plainneſſe, and brevity, unto which many are very attentive.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, if there be any occaſion, we in the next place go to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition and cenſure; unto which they ſubmit themſelves re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verently, and obediently, and ſome of them penitently confeſſing their ſins with much plainneſſe, and without ſhiftings, and excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: I will inſtance in two or three particulars; this was one caſe, a man named <hi>Wampoowas,</hi> being in a paſſion upon ſome light occaſion did beat his wife, which was a very great offence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them now (though in former times it was very uſuall) and they had made a Law againſt it, and ſet a fine upon it; whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he was publikly brought forth before the Aſſembly, which was great that day, for our Governor and many other Engliſh were then preſent: the man wholly condemned himſelf without any excuſe: and when he was asked what provocation his wife gave him? he did not in the leaſt meaſure blame her but himſelf, and when the quality of the ſinne was opened, that it was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty to his own body, and againſt Gods Commandement, and that paſſion was a ſinne, and much aggravated by ſuch effects, yet God was ready to pardon it in Chriſt, &amp;c. he turned his face to the wall and wept, though with modeſt indeavor to hide it; and ſuch was the modeſt, penitent, and melting behaviour of the man, that it much affected all to ſee it in a Barbarian, and all did forgive him, onely this remained, that they executed their Law notwithſtanding his repentance, and required his fine, to which he willingly ſubmitted, and paid it.</p>
               <p>Another caſe of admonition was this, <hi>Cutſhamaquin</hi> the <hi>Sachim</hi> having aſon of about 14 or 15 yeers old, he had bin drunk, &amp; had behaved himſelf diſobediently, and rebelliouſly againſt his father and mother, for which ſinne they did blame him, but he deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their admonition. And before I knew of it, I did obſerve when I catechized him, when he ſhould ſay the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he did not freely ſay, <hi>Honor thy father,</hi> but wholly left out <hi>mother,</hi> and ſo he did the Lecture day before, but when this ſinne of his was produced, he was called forth before the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117534:19"/> and hee confeſſed that what was ſaid againſt him was true, but hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h to accuſe his father of ſundry evils, as that hee would have killed him in his anger, and that he forced him to drink Sack, and I know not what elſe: which behavior wee greatly diſliked, ſhewed him the evill of it, and Mr. <hi>Wilſon</hi> being preſent laboured much with him, for hee underſtood the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, but all in vaine, his l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>art was hard and hopeleſſe for that time, therefore uſing due loving perſwaſions, wee did ſharply admoniſh him of his ſinne, and required him to anſwer further the next Lecture day, and ſo left him; and ſo ſtout he was, that when his father offered to pay his fine of 10 s. for his drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe according to their Law, he would not except it at his hand. When the next day was come, and other exerciſes finiſhed, I called him forth, and he willingly came, but ſtill in the ſame mind as before. Then wee turned to his father, and exhorted him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move that ſtumbling block out of his ſonnes way, by confeſſing his own ſinnes whereby hee had given occaſion of hardneſſe of heart to his ſonne; which thing was not ſuddain to him, for I had formerly in private prepared him thereunto, and hee was very willing to hearken to that counſell, becauſe his conſcience told him he was blameworthy; and accordingly he did, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed his maine and principall evils of his own accord: and upon this advantage I took occaſion to put him upon confeſſion of ſundry other vices which I knew hee had in former times been guilty of, and all the Indians knew it likewiſe; and put it after this manner, Are you now ſorry for your drunkeneſſe, filthines, falſe dealing, lying, &amp;c. which ſinnes you committed before you knew God? unto all which caſes, he expreſſed himſelf ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and condemned himſelf for them: which example of the <hi>Sachim</hi> was profitable for all the Indians. And when he had thus confeſſed his ſinnes, we turned againe to his ſonne and laboured with him, requiring him to confeſſe his ſinne, and intreat God to forgive him for Chriſt his ſake, and to confeſſe his offence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his father and mother, and intreat them to forgive him, but he ſtill refuſed; and now the other Indians ſpake unto him ſoberly, and affectionatly, to put him on, and divers ſpake one after another, and ſome ſeverall times. Mr. <hi>Wilſon</hi> againe did much labour with him, and at laſt he did humble himſelf, confeſſed all,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117534:19"/> and intreated his father to forgive him, and took him by the hand, at which his father burſt forth into great weeping: hee did the ſame alſo to his mother, who wept alſo, and ſo did di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others; and many Engliſh being preſent, they fell a weeping, ſo that the houſe was filled with weeping on every ſide; and then we went to prayer, in all which time <hi>Cutſhamaquin</hi> wept, in ſo much that when wee had done the board he ſtood upon was all dropped with his teares.</p>
               <p>Another caſe of admonition was this, a hopefull young man who is my ſervant, being upon a journey, and drinking Sack at their ſetting forth, he drank too much, and was diſguiſed; which when I heard I reproved him, and he humbled himſelf, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of his ſinne, and teares. And the next Lecture day I called him forth before the Aſſembly, where he did confeſſe his ſinne with many teares.</p>
               <p>Before I leave this point of admonition, if I thought it would not bee two tedious to you, I would mention one particular more, where we ſaw the power of God awing a wicked wretch by this ordinance of admonition. It was <hi>George</hi> that wicked <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian,</hi> who as you know, at our firſt beginnings ſought to caſt aſperſions upon Religion, by laying ſlanderous accuſations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt godly men, and who asked that captious queſtion, <hi>who made Sack?</hi> and this fellow having kild a young Cow at your Towne, and ſold it at the Colledge inſtead of <hi>Mooſe,</hi> covered it with many lies, inſomuch as Mr. <hi>Dunſter</hi> was loath he ſhould be directly charged with it when we called him forth, but that wee ſhould rather inquire. But when he was called b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fore the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and charged with it, he had not power to deny it, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently confeſſed, onely hee added one thing which wee think was an excuſe; thus God hath honored this ordinance among them.</p>
               <p>Fourthly the laſt exerciſe, you know, we have among them, is their asking us queſtions, and very many they have asked, which I have forgotten but ſome few that come to my preſent remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance I will briefly touch.</p>
               <p>One was <hi>Wabb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ko<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ets</hi> queſtion, who is reputed an old <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ww<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> it was to this purpoſe, ſeeing the Engliſh had been 27. yeers (ſome of them) in this land, why did wee never teach them to know
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117534:20"/> God till now? had you done it ſooner, ſaid hee, wee might have known much of God by this time, and much ſin might have been prevented, but now ſome of us are grown old in fin, &amp;c. To whom we anſwered, that we doe repent that wee did not long agoe, as now we doe, yet withall wee told them, that they were never wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to hear till now, and that ſeeing God hath bowed their hearts to be willing to hear, we are deſirous to take all the paines we can now to teach them.</p>
               <p>Another queſtion was, that of <hi>Cutſhamaquin,</hi> to this purpoſe, Before I knew God, ſaid he, I thought I was well, but ſince I have known God and ſin, I find my heartfull of ſin, and more ſinfull then ever it was before, and this hath been a great trouble to mee; and at this day my heart is but very little better then it was, and I am afraid it will be as bad againe as it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and therefore I ſometime wiſh I might die before I be ſo bad again as I have been. Now my queſtion is, whether is this a ſin or not? This queſtion could not be learned from the Engliſh, nor did it ſeem a coyned ſeigned thing, but a reall matter gathered from the experience of his own heart, and from an inward obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of himſelf.</p>
               <p>Another queſtion was about their children, Whither their little children goe when they dye, ſeeing they have not ſinned?</p>
               <p>Which queſtion gave occaſion more fully to teach them ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſin, and the damned ſtate of all men: And alſo, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially it gave occaſion to teach them the Covenant of God, which he hath made with all his people, and with their children, ſo that when God chooſes a man or a woman to be his ſervant, he chooſes all their children to be ſo alſo: which doctrin was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding gratefull unto them.</p>
               <p>Another great queſtion was this, when I preached out of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 9, 10, 11. old Mr. <hi>Brown,</hi> being preſent, obſerved them to be much affected, and one eſpecially did weep very much, though covered it what hee could; and after that there was a generall queſtion, which they ſent unto mee about, by my man, as the queſtion of them all, <hi>Whether any of them ſhould goe to Heaven, ſeeing they found their hearts full of ſinne, and eſpecially full of the ſinne of luſt,</hi> which they call <hi>nanwunwudſquas,</hi> that is, mad after women; and the next meeting, being at <hi>Dorcheſter mill,</hi> Mr. <hi>Mather</hi> and Mr.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117534:20"/> 
                  <hi>Wareham,</hi> with divers others being preſent, they did there pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it, expreſſing their feares, <hi>that none of them ſhould bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved;</hi> which queſtion did draw forth my heart to preach and preſſe the promiſe of pardon to all that were weary and ſick of ſinne, if they did beleeve in Chriſt who had died for us, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied the juſtice of God for all our ſinnes, and through whom God is well pleaſed with all ſuch repenting ſinners that come to Chriſt, and beleeve in him; and the next day I took that Text, <hi>Matih.</hi> 11. 28, 29. and this doctrin ſome of them in a ſpeciall manner did receive in a very reverent manner.</p>
               <p>There is another great queſtion that hath been ſeverall times propounded, and much ſticks w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch as begin to pray, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>If they leave off</hi> Powwawing, <hi>and pray to God, what ſhall they do when they are ſick?</hi> for they have no skill in phyſick, though ſome of them underſtand the vertues of ſundry things, yet the ſtate of mans body, and skill to apply them they have not: but all the refuge they have and relie upon in time of ſickneſſe is their <hi>Powwaws,</hi> who by antick, fooliſh and irrationall conceits delude the poore people; ſo that it is a very needfull thing to informe them in the uſe of Phyſick, and a moſt effectuall meanes to take them off from their <hi>Powwawing.</hi> Some of the wiſer ſort I have ſtirred up to get this skill; I have ſhewed them the anatomy of mans body, and ſome generall principles of Phyſick, which is very acceptable to them, but they are ſo extreamely igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that theſe things muſt rather be taught by ſight, ſenſe, and experiance then by precepts, and rules of art; and therefore I have had many thoughts in my heart, that it were a ſingular good work, if the Lord would ſtirre up the hearts of ſome or other of his people in England to give ſome maintenance toward ſome Schoole or Collegiate exerciſe this way, wherein there ſhould be Anatomies and other inſtructions that way, and where there might be ſome recompence given to any that ſhould bring in any vegetable or other thing that is vertuous in the way of Phyſick; by this means we ſhould ſoon have all theſe things which they know, and others of our Countreymen that are skilfull that way, and now their skill lies buried for want of incouragement, would be a ſearching and trying to find out the vertues of things in this countrey, which doubtleſſe are many, and would not a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117534:21"/> little conduce to the benefit of the people of this Countrey, and it may bee of our native Countrey alſo; by this meanes wee ſhould traine up theſe poore <hi>Indians</hi> in that skill which would confound and root out their <hi>Pawwaws,</hi> and then would they be fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re more eaſily inclined to leave thoſe wayes, and pray unto God, whoſe gift Phyſick is, and whoſe bleſſing muſt make it effectuall.</p>
               <p>There is alſo another reaſon which moves my thought and deſires this way, namely that our young Students in Phyſick may be trained up better then yet they bee, who have onely theoreticall knowledge, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> forced to fall to practiſe before ever they ſaw an Anatomy made, or duely trained up in making experiments, for we never had but one Anatomy in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, which Mr. <hi>Giles Firman</hi> (now in England) did make and read upon very well, but no more of that now.</p>
               <p>This very day that I wrote theſe things unto you, I have been with the <hi>Indians</hi> to teach them, as I was wont to doe, and one of their queſtions among many other was to know what to ſay to ſuch <hi>Indians</hi> as oppoſe their praying to God, and beleeving in Jeſus Chriſt, and for their own information alſo, What get you, ſay they, by praying to God, and beleeving in Jeſus Chriſt? you goe naked ſtill, and you are as poore as wee, and our Corne is as good as yours, and wee take more pleaſure then you; did we ſee that you got any thing by it, wee would pray to God and beleeve in Jeſus Chriſt alſo as you doe? Unto which queſtion I then anſwered them. Firſt, God giveth unto us two ſorts of good things, one ſort are little ones, which I ſhewed by my little finger; the other ſort are great ones, which I ſhewed by my thumbe, (for you know they uſe and delight in demonſtrations:) the little mercies are riches, as cloths, food, ſack, houſes, cattle, and pleaſures, theſe are little things which ſerve but for our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies a little while in this life; the great mercies are wiſdome, the knowledge of God, Chriſt, eternall life, repentance, faith, theſe are mercies for the ſoule, and for eternall life: now though God do not yet give you the little mercies, he giveth you that which is a great deale better, which the wicked <hi>Indians</hi> cannot ſee. And this I proved to them by this example; when <hi>Foxun</hi> the <hi>Mohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan</hi> Counſeller, who is counted the wiſeſt <hi>Indian</hi> in the Country,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117534:21"/> was in the <hi>Bay,</hi> I did on purpoſe bring him unto you; and when he was here, you ſaw he was a foole in compariſon of you, for you could ſpeak of God and Chriſt, and heaven and repentance and faith, but he ſate and had not one word to ſay, unleſſe you talked of ſuch poor things as hunting, wars, &amp;c. Secondly, you have ſome more cloths then they, and the reaſon why you have no more is becauſe you have but a little wiſdome, if you were more wiſe to know God, and obey his Commands, you would work more then you do, for to God commandeth, <hi>Six dayes thou ſhale work, &amp;c.</hi> and thus the Engliſh do: and if you would bee ſo wiſe as to worke as they do, you ſhould have cloths, houſes, cattle, riches as they have, God would give you them.</p>
               <p>This day they told me this news, that ſome of them having been abroad in the Country at <hi>Titacut,</hi> divers of thoſe <hi>Indians</hi> would be glad to know God, and to pray unto God, and would be glad if I would come and teach them, but ſome of them oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and would not. They askt me this day, why God made the Rainbow. Theſe things are now freſh in my mind, that makes me ſo large in them, but I'le forbeare any more of their queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this nature.</p>
               <p>There do ſundry times fall out differences among them, and they uſually bring their caſes to me, and ſometime ſuch, as it's needfull for me to decline; where I may, I adviſe them to ſome iſſue. One great caſe that hath come ſeverall times to mee, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſuch debts as they owe by gaming, for they have been great gameſters, but have moved queſtions about it, and are informed of the unlawfulneſſe of it, and have thereupon wholly given over gaming for any wagers, and all games wherein is a lot, onely uſe lawfull recreations, and have a Law againſt unlawfull gaming; but other <hi>Indians</hi> that are of another mind, come and challenge their old debts, and now they refuſe to pay, becauſe is was a ſinne ſo to game, and they now pray to God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt not pay ſuch ſinfull debts. Now the caſe being ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and ſuch as I ſaw a ſnare underneath, the firſt counſaile they had was, who ever would challenge ſuch a debt ſhould come to our Governor, and he would take order to rectifie the matter. But the Creditors liked not that way, and therefore ſoon after there came another caſe of the ſame kinde, and an iſſue was very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117534:22"/> therefore I firſt dealt with the creditor, and ſhewed him the ſinfulneſſe of ſuch games, and how angry God was at them; and therefore perſwaded him to be content to take half his debt, unto which he very willingly condeſcended; then I dealt with the debtor, and askt him if he did not promiſe to pay him all that debt? and he anſwered yea, he did ſo; then I ſhewed him that God commands us to performe our promiſes, and though be ſinned in gaming, he muſt repent of that, but ſeeing he hath promiſed payment, he ſhould ſin to break his promiſe: at which he was utterly ſilenced; but then I asked him, if hee would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly pay half, if I ſhould perſwade the other to accept it; yea ſaid hee very willingly, and ſo the matter ended: and in this way they uſually end ſuch caſes ſince that time. Their young men, who of all the reſt, live moſt idlely and diſſolutely, now begin to goe to ſervice, ſome to <hi>Indians,</hi> ſome to <hi>Fngliſh;</hi> and ſome of them growing weary, broak out of their ſervices, and they had no help among them for it; ſo that ſome propounded what they ſhould doe to remedy that evill; they were anſwered, that the Engliſh bring ſuch ſervants to the Court, and our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates rectifie thoſe evills; then they deſired that they might have a Court among them for government, at which motion wee rejoyced, ſeeing it came from themſelves, and tended ſo much to civilize them, ſince which time I moved the Generall Court in it, and they have pleaſed to order a way for exerciſing government among them: the good Lord proſper and bleſſe it.</p>
               <p>They moved alſo as you know for a School, and through Gods mercy a courſe is now taken that there be Schooles at both pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where their children are taught.</p>
               <p>You know likewiſe that wee exhorted them to ſence their ground with ditches, ſtone walls, upon the banks, and promiſed to helpe them with Shovels, Spades, Mattocks, Crows of Iron; and they are very deſirous to follow that counſell, and call upon me to help them with tooles faſter them I can get them, though I have now bought pretty ſtore, and they (I hope) are at work. The women are deſirous to learn to ſpin, and I have procured Wheels for ſundry of them, and they can ſpin pretty well. They begin to grow induſtrious, and find ſomething to ſell at Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket all the yeer long: all winter they ſell Brooms, Staves, Elepots,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117534:22"/> Baskets, Turkies. In the Spring, Cranebe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies, Fiſh, Stawberies, in the Summer Hurtleberries, Grapes, Fiſh: in the Autumn they ſell Craneberries, Fiſh, Veniſon, &amp;c. and they find a good benefit by the Market, and grow more and more to make uſe thereof; beſides ſundry of them work with the Engliſh in Hay time, and Harveſt, but yet it's not comparable to what they might do, if they were induſtrious, and old boughs muſt be bent a little at once; if we can ſet the young twiggs in a better bent, it will bee Gods mercy. Deare brother I can go no further, a weary body, and ſleepy eyes command me to conclude, if I have not ſatisfied your deſire in this little I have wrote, let me underſtand it from you, and I ſhall be willing to do my indeavour: and thus with my deare love remembred to your ſelf and your beloved yoakfellow, and deſiring your prayers for Gods grace and bleſſing upon my ſpirit and poor indeavours, I take leave at this time and reſt</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Roxbury <date>
                        <hi>this</hi> 24. of Septemb. 1647.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Tour loving brother in our Saviour Chriſt, JOHN ELIOT.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Let me adde this Poſtſcript, that there be two reaſons that make me beleeve the Lords time is come to make a preparative at leaſt for the comming of his grace, and kingdome among them. Firſt, that he hath bowed their hearts, who were as averſe, and as farre off from God, as any heathen in the world; and their hearts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to bow more and more. Secondly, becauſe the Lord hath raiſed a mighty ſpirit of prayer in this behalfe in all the Churches.</p>
               <p>This Relation of Mr.<hi>Eliots</hi> I know many things therein to be true, &amp; all the reſt I have heard confirmed by credible perſons, eye &amp; eare witneſſes oftheſe things, and they are familiarly known in theſe parts. I know alſo that Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> writes (as his ſpirit is) modeſtly and ſparingly, and ſpeaks the leaſt in ſundry particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars; for in his ſtory of the repentance and publike admonition of his own man, page 23. hee ſaith he manifeſted many teares in publike, but I heard it from many then preſent that there were ſo many, as that the dry place of the <hi>Wigmom,</hi> where hee ſtood
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117534:23"/> was bedirtied with them, powring them out ſo abundantly. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> are well known not to bee much ſubject to teares, no not when they come to feele the ſoreſt torture, or are ſolemnly brought forth to die; and if the Word workes theſe teares, ſurely there is ſome conquering power of Chriſt Jeſus ſtirring among them, which what it will end in at laſt, the Lord belt knows. If Mr. <hi>Brigbtmans</hi> interpretation of <hi>Daniels</hi> propheſie be true, that <hi>Anno</hi> 1650. Europe will hear ſome of the beſt tidings that ever came into the world, <hi>viz.</hi> rumors from the Eaſterne Jews, which ſhall trouble the Turkiſh tyrant and ſhake his Pillars when they are comming to repoſſeſſe their own land, for which they will be wraſtling (if my memory failes not, according to his notion) about 40. yeers; I ſhall hope then that theſe Weſterne <hi>Indians</hi> will ſoon come in, and that theſe beginnings are but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratives for a brighter day then we yet ſee among them, wherein Eaſt &amp; Weſt ſhall ſing the ſong of the Lambe: but I have no skill in propheſies, nor do I beleeve every mans interpretation of ſuch Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; but this is certain, God is at work among theſe; and it is not uſual for the Sun to ſet as ſoon as it begins to riſe, nor for the Lord to Jeſus to loſe an inch of ground in the recovering times of his Churches peace and his own eclipſed and forgotten glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, (if theſe bee ſuch times) untill hee hath won the whole field, and driven the Prince of darkneſſe out of it, who is but a bold uſurper of the Lord Jeſus inheritance, to whom are given the utmoſt ends of the earth. When <hi>Charles</hi> the Great had bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the chief power of the barbarous and fierce <hi>Saxons</hi> in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> he made this the onely article of peace, that they ſhould entertain ſuch a Goſpel as good then as the degenerate Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an world could affoord, and for that end admit of a Monaſtery among them of ſuch men as might inſtruct them, and this courſe prevailed, if wee may beleeve <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Crantzius lib. ch.</hi> 1, 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Crantzius</hi> the Hiſtorian of thoſe times, and ſhall wee think that when the Lord Jeſus hath ſet up not a Monaſtery of workes but Churches of Saints in theſe toaſts to encourage the miniſtry and this work of Chriſt, that his bleſſed Goſpel cannot or ſhall not in theſe dayes take ſome effect ſince it hath broke ſo far? I dare conclude nothing, onely it will be our comfort in the day of our accounts, that wee have endeavored ſomething this way; and it may be this very indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117534:23"/> ſhall be our peace. <hi>Gildas</hi> our Britiſh Hiſtorian obſerving that one cauſe why God let looſe the <hi>Saxons</hi> to ſcourge and root out the <hi>Britaines,</hi> was their deep careleſneſſe of communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, unto them the Chriſtian Religion, when they had their ſpirits at fit advantage: but I dare not diſcourſe of theſe matters.</p>
               <p>One thing more I remember concerning Mr. <hi>Eliots</hi> conference with a <hi>Narraganſet Sachim</hi> a ſober man this yeer; after that he had taught this <hi>Sachim</hi> the Law of God and had ſhewen Lim the means of ſalvation by Chriſt; he then asked him if he did know And underſtand thoſe things? and heſaid, yes. He then asked him if he did beleeve them? but hee could not get any anſwer from him that way, but did ſeeme to take them into more ſerious thoughts. He then asked him, why they did not learn of Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> who hath lived among them divers yeers? and he ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly anſwered that they did not care to learn of him, becauſe hee is no good man but goes out and workes upon the Sabbath day; I name it not to ſhew what glimmerings nature may have concerning the obſervation of the Sabbath, but to ſhew what the ill example of Engliſh may doe, and to ſee what a ſtumbling block to all Religion the looſe obſervation of the Sabbath is, however mans ſhifting wits may find out evaſions, to get looſe from out of that net.</p>
               <p>But this may ſerve to ſatisfie your own or others deſires con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the progreſſe of the Goſpel among the <hi>Indians:</hi> the Lord Jeſus ſeemes at this day to bee turning upſide down the whole frame of things in the world, Kings Parliaments, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Kingdomes, Authorities, Churches, Miniſters, and if out of his free grace hee looks not upon theſe hopefull beginnings, theſe will be ſo turned alſo; for oppoſition there is from men and devils againſt it, and I have feared in my own heart that within theſe few moneths there hath been ſome coolings among the beſt of theſe <hi>Indians;</hi> but wee find it ſo alſo among ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny people that are <hi>Engliſh</hi> in their firſt work, but the Lord Jeſus revives again; and therefore Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> of late having told them that hee was afraid that they began to bee weary. they took it to heart, and propounded in my hearing at a late <hi>Indian</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture at <hi>Noonanetum</hi> many profitable queſtions, viz. <hi>When they
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117534:24"/> prayed and heard the Word aright? and how they might know when they were weary of them? And what time it might bee before the Lord might come and make them know him? And what the firſt ſinne of the Devils was?</hi> (Hee diſcourſing to them about the danger of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie) At this time they are (as you may perceive by Mr. <hi>Eliots</hi> writings) about fencing in their ground and Town given them ſome hundreds of Acres, with a ſtone fence, for which end Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> provides them Mattocks, Shovels and Crowes of Iron, &amp;c. and to encourage their ſlothfulneſſe, promiſed to give a groat or ſix pence a rod, if they would thus farre attend their own good, and work for themſelves: all the poor <hi>Indians at Noonane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> are generally clad with ſuch cloths as wee can get them, and the <hi>Wigwams</hi> of the meaneſt of them equallize any <hi>Sachims</hi> in other places, being built not with mats but barks of Trees in good bigneſſe, the rather that they may have their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions in them for husbands and wives togeather, and their children and ſervants in their places alſo, who formerly were never private in what nature is aſhamed of, either for the ſun or any man to ſee. It's ſome refreſhing to thinke that there is (if there was no more but) the name of Chriſt ſounding in thoſe darke and deſpicable <hi>Tartarian</hi> Tents; the Lord can build them houſes in time to pray in, when hee hath given unto them bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hearts, and when perhaps hee hath curſed and conſumed theirs who have diſdained to give that worſhip and homage to Chriſt in their ſeiled houſes, which poor <hi>Indians</hi> rejoyee to give to him in their poor Tents and <hi>Wigwams:</hi> I deſire you to gather what ſtock of prayers you can for them. I had almoſt forgot to tell you of Mr. <hi>Eliots</hi> going up the Country lately with Mr. <hi>Flint,</hi> Captain <hi>Willard</hi> of <hi>Concord,</hi> and ſundry others, towards <hi>Merrimath</hi> River unto that <hi>Indian Sachim Paſſaconna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> that old Witch and <hi>Powwaw,</hi> who together with both his ſons, fled the preſence of the light, and durſt not ſtand their ground, nor be at home when he came, pretending feare of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing killed by a man forſooth that came only with a book in his hand, and with a few others without any weapons only to bear him company and direct his way in thoſe deſerts, but in it you may ſee the guilt of the man, &amp; that <hi>Satan</hi> is but a coward in his <hi>Lyons</hi> skin even upon his own dunghill, as alſo the hatred and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:117534:24"/> enmity againſt the Word which is in ſome, which argues that the attention which others give to it, is a power of God, and not meerly to flatter and get favour with the Engliſh: but the reſt of <hi>Paſſaconnawaies</hi> men attended to the things which were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and asked divers queſtions, the <hi>Indians</hi> in our parts accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panying Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> and giving bleſſed examples to the others herein, as alſo in ſaying Grace before and after meat, praying in their <hi>Wigwams</hi> with them, and ſome of them ſinging of Pſalmes, which they have learnt among the Engliſh: diſcourſing alſo with them about the things of God. It is ſomewhat obſervable (though the obſervation bee more cheerfull then deep) that the firſt Text out of which Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> preached to the <hi>Indians</hi> was about the dry bones, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37. where it's ſaid, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 9, 10. <hi>that by propbeſying to the wind, the wind came and the dry bones lived;</hi> now the <hi>Indian</hi> word for Wind is <hi>Waubon,</hi> and the moſt active <hi>Indian</hi> for ſtirring up other <hi>Indians</hi> to ſeek after the knowledg of God in theſe parts, his name is <hi>Waubon,</hi> which ſignifies Wind, (the <hi>Indians</hi> giving names to their children uſually according to appearances of providences) although they never dreamt of this, that this their <hi>Waubon</hi> ſhould breathe ſuch a ſpirit of life and incouragement in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the reſt of the <hi>Indians.</hi> as hee hath indeavored in all parts of the Countrey, both at <hi>Concord, Merrimeek</hi> and elſewhere; but ſome of the <hi>Indians</hi> themſelves that were ſtir'd up by him took notice of this his name and that Scripture together, and the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh alſo have much obſerved him herein, who ſtill continues the ſame man, although we thinke there be now many others whom he firſt breathed encouragement into that do farre exceed him in the light and life of the things of God: Mr.<hi>Eliot</hi> alſo profeſſing that he choſe that Text without the leaſt thought of any ſuch application in reſpect of <hi>Waubon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There have been many difficult queſtions propounded by them, which we have been unwilling to engage our ſelves in any an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer unto, untill wee have the concurrence of others with ns.</p>
               <p>Firſt, ſuppoſe a man before hee knew God, hath had two wives, the firſt barren and childleſſe, the ſecond fruitfull and bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him many ſweet children, the queſtion now propounded was, <hi>which of theſe two wives he is to put away?</hi> if hee puts away; the firſt who hath no children, then hee puts away her whom God and Religion undoubtedly binds him unto, there
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:117534:25"/> being no other defect but want of children: if hee puts away the other, then he muſt caſt off all his children with her alſo as illegitimate, whom hee ſo exceedingly loves. This is a caſe now among them, and they are very fearefull to do any thing croſſe to Gods will and mind herein.</p>
               <p>Secondly, ſuppoſe a man marry a <hi>Sqaw,</hi> and ſhee deſerts and flies from her husband, and commits adultery with other remote <hi>Indians,</hi> but afterward it come to paſſe that ſhee hearing the Word, and ſorry for what ſhee hath done, ſhe deſires to come to her husband againe, who remaines ſtill unmarried; <hi>Whether ſhould this husband upon her repentance receive her againe? and whether in be not bound thereunto ſo to doe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At the laſt Lecture at <hi>Noonanetum</hi> this <hi>September,</hi> there were divers queſtions asked: one was propounded by an old <hi>Sqaw,</hi> a Widow; viz. <hi>If when men know God, God loves them, why then is it that any one are afflicted after that they know him?</hi> I ſhall men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion no more, but conclude with the ſolemn ſpeech of a ſober and hopefull <hi>Indian</hi> at this Lecture, whoſe name is <hi>Wampooas,</hi> who in ſtead of propounding a queſtion fell into theſe expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, viz. <q>That becauſe wee pray to God, other <hi>Indians</hi> abroad in the countrey hate us and oppoſe us, the Engliſh on the other ſide ſuſpect us, and feare us to be ſtill ſuch as doe not pray at all; but (ſaith he) God who knowes all things, he knowes that wee do pray to him.</q> To which ſpeech Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> replyed, that it was true indeed, that ſome of the Engliſh did ſo far ſuſpect them for ſundry reaſons; but I doe not ſo, and others of us, who know you and ſpeake with you, we do not ſo think of you; and then gave them gracious and ſerious incouragements to goe forward and make more progreſſe in the things of God. This their own teſtimony of themſelves being propounded with much ſweetneſſe and ſeriouſneſſe of affection, may be the laſt, although it be the leaſt confirmation of ſome inward worke among them; which I looked upon as a ſpeciall providence that ſuch a ſpeech ſhould be ſpoken and come to my eare juſt at ſuch a time as this, wherein I was finiſhing the ſtory, to confirme in ſome meaſure what hath been written; the Lord himſelf I beleeve and no man living, putting theſe words into their own hearts, to give this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt teſtimony concerning themſelves. The beginning of this enlargement of Chriſts Kingdome ſhould inlarge our hearts with
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:117534:25"/> great joy. If I ſhould gather and ſumme up together the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall gracious impreſſions of God upon them from what hath been ſcattered here and there in the ſtory, I thinke it might make many Chriſtians aſhamed, who may eaſily ſee how farre they are exceeded by theſe naked men in ſo ſhort a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ime thus wrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by ſuch ſmall and deſpicable means. My brother <hi>Eliot</hi> who is Preacher to them, proſelling he can as yet but ſtammer out ſome peeces of the Word of God unto them in their own tongue; but God is with him, and God is wont to be <hi>maximus in minimis,</hi> and is moſt ſeene in doing great things by ſmall meanes. The Sword of Gods Word ſhall and will pierce deep, even when it is half broken, when the hand of a mighty Redeemer hath the laying of it on: and the Scripture herein is, and muſt be fulfilled, that as ſoon as the heathen heare Chriſt they ſhall ſubmit, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. 43, 44. and ſuch nations whom Chriſt knew not ſhall run unto him, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 55. 5. The fall of the unbeleving Jewes was the riſing of the Gentiles; my prayer to God therefore for <hi>Europe</hi> is, that the fall of the Churches, (little bettered by the devouring Sword which is ſtill thirſty) may not bee the riſing of theſe <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rican</hi> Gentiles, never pitied till now. I wiſh that <hi>Alſted ius</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie <note place="margin">Alſted in Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t,</note> herein may never prove true; but rather that the riſing of theſe may be a provoking and raiſing up of them, eſpecially of the Engliſh, to lament after that God whom they have forſaken; and to lament after him, together with us, for theſe poor <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> who never yet knew him.</p>
               <p>Sir, I had ended theſe relations once or twice, but the ſtay of the Veſſell increaſeth new matter; which becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>is new and freſh, you ſhall have it as I heard of it from a faithfull hand: There were ſundry queſtions propounded at the <hi>Indian</hi> Lecture at <hi>Noonanetum</hi> this <hi>Octob.</hi> 13. by the <hi>Indians:</hi> the firſt was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to Mr. <hi>Eliot</hi> himſelf upon occaſion of his Sermon out of <hi>Epheſ. 5. 11. Have no fellowſhip with unfruitfull workers of darknes,</hi> viz. <hi>What Engliſh men did thinke of</hi> Mr. Eliot <hi>becauſe be came among wicked Indians to teach them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Suppoſe two men ſinne, the one knowes be ſinneth, and the other doth not know ſinne, will God puniſh both alike?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Suppoſe there ſhould be one wiſe Indian that teacheth good things to other Indians, whether ſhould not he be as a father or brother unto
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:117534:26"/> ſuch Indians he ſo teacheth in the wayes of God?</hi> This laſt queſtion ſeemes to argue ſome motions ſtirring in ſome of their hearts to pity and teach their poor Countreymen; and ſurely then will bee the moſt hopefull time of doing good among them, when the Lord ſhall raiſe up ſome or other like themſelves to go among them and preach the Word of life unto them with fatherly or brotherly bowels; and yet I limit not the moſt High, who can make uſe of what Inſtruments hee pleaſeth for this work. I ſhall conclude therefore with a ſtory I had both by writing and word of mouth, from a faithfull <note n="*" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Edward Jackſon.</hi>
                  </note> man which hee ſaw with his own eyes this <hi>Octob.</hi> 7. There was one of the <hi>Indians</hi> at <hi>Noonane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> hath had a child ſick of a Conſumption many a day, and at that time died of it; when it was dead, ſome of the <hi>Indians</hi> came to an honeſt man to enquire how they ſhould bury their dead; the man told them how and what the Engliſh did when they buried theirs; hereupon rejecting all their old ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous obſervances at ſuch ſad times (which are not a few) they preſently procured a few boards, and buy a few <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>yles of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and ſo make a pretty handſome Coffin, (for they are very dextrous at any thing they ſee once done) and put the child in to it, and ſo accompanied it to the grave very ſolemnly, about 40. <hi>Indians</hi> of them: when the earth was caſt upon it and the grave made up, they withdrew a little from that place, and went all together and aſſembled under a Tree in the Woods, and there they deſired one <hi>Tutaſwampe</hi> a very hopefull <hi>Indian</hi> to pray with them; now although the <hi>Engliſh</hi> do not uſually meet in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies to pray together after ſuch ſad occaſions, yet it ſeemes God ſtird up their hearts thus to doe; what the ſubſtance of their prayer was I cannot certainly learn, although I have heard ſome things that way, which I therefore name not, onely I have and ſhall indeavour to get it, if it bee poſſible for the poor <hi>Indian</hi> to expreſſe the ſubſtance of it, and ſo ſhall ſend it if the ſhip ſtayes long, onely this is certaine by him who was occaſionally an eye and care witneſſe of theſe things, that they continued inſtant with God in prayer for almoſt half an houre together, and this godly mans words to mee (who underſtands a little of their lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage) are theſe; that this <hi>Tutaſwampe</hi> did expreſſe ſuch zeale in prayer with ſuch variety of gracious expreſſions, and abundance
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:117534:26"/> of teares, both of himſelf and moſt of the company, that the woods rang againe with their ſighes and prayers; and (ſaith he) I was much aſhamed of my ſelf and ſome others, that hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> had ſo great light, and yet want ſuch affections as they have, who have as yet ſo little knowledge. All this he ſaw ſtanding at ſome good diſtance alone from them under a Tree.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee (Sir) that theſe old obdurate ſinners are not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſenſeleſſe of Gods afflicting hand and humbling providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and though naturall affection may be much ſtirring in ſuch times, yet you ſee how God begins to ſanctifie ſuch affections among them: and I wiſh that many Engliſh were not outſtript herein by theſe poor <hi>Indians,</hi> who have got the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>art I ſeare of many <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that can paſſe by ſuch ſad providences without laying them in this manner to heart. I confeſſe theſe and many ſuch things which wee ſee in divers of them, do make ſome to thinke that there is more of God and his Spirit in ſome of their hearts then we yet can diſcover, and which they hope will break out in time.</p>
               <p>Thus you have a true, but ſomewhat rent and ragged relation of theſe things; it may be moſt ſutable to the ſtory of naked and rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged men: my deſire is that no mans Spectacles may deceive him, ſo as to look upon theſe things either as bigger or leſſer, better or worſer then they are; which all men generally are apt to doe at things at ſo great diſtance, but that they may judge of them as indeed they are, by what truth they ſee here expreſt in the things themſelves. I know that ſome thinke that all this worke among them is done and acted thus by the <hi>Indians</hi> to pleaſe the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and for applauſe from them; and it is not unlikely but ſo'tis in many, who doe but blaze for a time; but certainly'tis not ſo in all, but that the power of the Word hath taken place in ſome, and that inwardly and effectually, but how far ſavingly time will declare, and the reader may judge of, by the ſtory itſelf of theſe things. Some ſay that if it be ſo, yet they are but a few that are thus wrought upon; Be it ſo, yet ſo it hath ever been, <hi>many called, few choſen:</hi> and yet withall I beleeve the calling in of a few Indians to Chriſt is the gathering home of many hundreds in one, conſidering what a vaſt diſtance there hath been between God and them ſo long, even dayes without number; conſidering
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:117534:27"/> alſo how precious the firſt fruits of <hi>America</hi> will be to Jeſus Chriſt, and what ſeeds they may be of great harveſts in after times; and yet if there was no great matter ſeen in theſe of grown yeers, their children notwithſtanding are of great hopes both from <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Indians</hi> themſelves, who are therefore trained up to Schoole, where many are very apt to learne, and who are alſo able readily to anſwer to the queſtions propounded, containing the principles and grounds of all Chriſtian Religion in their own tongue. I confeſſe it paſſeth my skill to tell how the Goſpel ſhould be generally received by theſe <hi>American</hi> Natives, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the variety of Languages in ſmall diſtances of places; onely hee that made their eares and tongues can raiſe up ſome or other to teach them how to heare, and what to ſpake; and if the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel muſt ride circuit, Chriſt can and will conquer by weake and deſpicable meanes, though the conqueſt perhaps may be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what long. The beginnings and foundations of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> in the Southerne parts of this vaſt continent, being laid in the blood of nineteene Millions of poor innocent Natives (as <hi>Acoſta</hi> the Jeſuite a bird of their own neſt relates the ſtory) ſhall certainly therefore bee utterly rooted up by ſome revenging hand; and when he is once diſpoſſeſt of his Golden Manſions and Silver Mines, it may be then the oppreſſed remnant in thoſe coaſts al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo may come in. In the meane while if it bee the good pleaſure of Chriſt to look upon any of the worſt and meaneſt of theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſts in theſe Coaſts of <hi>New-England,</hi> let us not deſpiſe this day of ſmall things, but as the Jews did of old, ſo let us now cry mightily to God and ſay, and ſing, <hi>Let the people praiſe thee O God, yea let all the people praiſe thee, then ſhall the earth bringforth her increaſe, and God even our God will bleſſe us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have ſent you two witneſſes beſide my own of the truth of the Indian ſtory printed, you may publiſh them if you pleaſe as they have writ, and ſubſcrib'd with their own hands.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>THOMAS SHEPHARD.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:117534:27"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
